<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ornaments for the daughters of Zion, or, The character and happiness of a virtuous woman in a disocurse which directs the female-sex how to express the fear of God in every age and state of their life, and obtain both temporal and eternal blessedness / written by Cotton Mather.</title>
            <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B26645</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18472297</idno>
  <idno type="VID">206531</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240851713</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1136</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">18472297</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B26645)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 206531)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1639:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ornaments for the daughters of Zion, or, The character and happiness of a virtuous woman in a disocurse which directs the female-sex how to express the fear of God in every age and state of their life, and obtain both temporal and eternal blessedness / written by Cotton Mather.</title>
                  <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 144 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [7]-[12].</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Women --  Religious life.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Christian life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:206531:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ornaments for the Daughters of</hi> Zion.</p>
            <p>Or the Character and Happiness of a Virtuous Woman: In a DISCOURSE Which directs the FEMALE-SEX how to express THE FEAR OF GOD in every <hi>Age</hi> and <hi>State</hi> of their LIFE; and obtain both <hi>Temporal</hi> and <hi>Eternal</hi> Blessedness.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>COTTON MATHER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullian's</hi> Advice for the Ornaments of WOMEN.</p>
            <q>Prodite Vos jam Ornamentis Extractae Apostolorum—Vestite Vos Serico Pietatis. Byssico Sanctitatis, Purpurâ Pudicitiae—Deum babebitis Amatorem.
<p>In English.</p> Go ye forth now array'd with such <hi>Ornaments</hi> as the <hi>Apostles</hi> have provided for you; Cloath your selves with the <hi>Silk</hi> of Piety, the <hi>Sattin</hi> of Sanctity, the <hi>Purple</hi> of Modesty; so the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God will be a <hi>Lover</hi> of you.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurst</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> the lower End of <hi>Cheapside.</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:206531:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:206531:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Most Virtuous and Accomplish'd THE Lady <hi>Elizabeth Rich.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>This Pattern of her own <hi>Character</hi> and <hi>Happiness</hi> is most Humbly Dedicated.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:206531:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:206531:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>'TIS very surprizing to see and read, what a <hi>[Mundus,</hi> or] World of Pretended ORNAMENTS, the Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> sets out <hi>The Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Zion,</hi> which liv'd in <hi>his</hi> Days, as <hi>Rigg'd</hi> withal. But among all those One and twenty <hi>Ornaments,</hi> I find none of those which the Inspired Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> does Recommend unto the <hi>Women</hi> of all Ages, as <hi>Things in the sight of God of great price.</hi> And therefore as I did not wonder at the following Menace of the Almighty, <hi>I will take away the Bravery of their Ornaments;</hi> thus I also set my self to accommodate my Neighbours, with such <hi>Ornaments,</hi> as make up what
<pb facs="tcp:206531:4"/>
               <hi>Mary</hi> Chose, even, <hi>The good part which cannot be taken away.</hi> They that shall Criminate an Ʋndertaking to write a little Book for promoting the <hi>Fear of God.</hi> in the <hi>Female Sex,</hi> do but shew their Ignorance of what was' done by <hi>Tertullian,</hi> by <hi>Jerom,</hi> by <hi>Austin</hi> in the Primitive Times, besides what has been done by several Renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Pens of a <hi>later Date;</hi> and perhaps they forget, That one Book in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Bible was written for <hi>An Elect Lady.</hi> As for the <hi>Manner</hi> of my own Writing, 'tis <hi>Plain, Brief, Chast;</hi> and not without an endeavour to imagine how such a Subject would have been handled by a <hi>Timothy,</hi> who was to address <hi>Women,</hi> and yet be an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Purity.</hi> But as for the <hi>Design</hi> of my Writing, 'tis <hi>purely</hi> to advance <hi>Virtue</hi> among those, <hi>who cannot forget their Ornaments,</hi> and yet often <hi>forget</hi> those things which are no less <hi>Necessary</hi> than <hi>Ornamental.</hi> Now may GOD prosper it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:206531:4"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Tho Park<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurst</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Cheapside</hi> near <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers Chappel.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Body of Practical Divinity, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting of above One Hundred Sermons on the Lesser Catechism of the Reverend Assembly of Divines at <hi>Westminster;</hi> with a Supplement of some Sermons on several Texts of Scripture. By <hi>Tho. Watson,</hi> formerly Minister of St. <hi>Stephens Walbrook.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Spirutal Mindedness.</p>
            <p>Person of Christ.</p>
            <p>A Discourse on 130th. <hi>Psalm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Doctrine of the Trinity.</p>
            <p>Of Mortification of Sin in Believers.</p>
            <p>An Humble Testimony concerning the Goodness and Severity of God in Dealing with sinful Churches and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>A Treatise of Temptation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:206531:5"/>
            <p>Eshcol. or Rules of Fellowship. These Eight last by <hi>John Owen</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heywoods</hi> Baptismal Bonds renewed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grotius</hi> of Christs Satisfaction, in English.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hursts</hi> Revival of Grace, <hi>i. e.</hi> on the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>The good of Early Obedience.</p>
            <p>A Sermon of Unity.</p>
            <p>The Vision of the Wheels in three Sermons.</p>
            <p>Spiritual Wisdom improved against Temptation.</p>
            <p>The almost Christian discovered. All Five by <hi>Mat. Mead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Consolation for the Afflicted, at the Funeral of Mr. <hi>Edward Rede.</hi> By <hi>Tim. Rogers.</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calamy</hi>'s Godly-Mans-Ark in five Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, his Art of Divine Meditation.</p>
            <p>Redemption of Time, the Wisdom and Duty of Christians in Evil days. By <hi>John Wade</hi> Minister at <hi>Hammer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Intercourses of Divine Love betwixt Christ and his Church on the Ist. and 2d. Chapters of the <hi>Canticles</hi> or the <hi>Song of Songs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:206531:5"/>
            <p>Several Discourses of actual Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in three Parts. These two last by <hi>John Collings</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>Spiritual Songs, or Songs of praise to Almighty God on several occasions with thirty Penitential Cries; with a Poem also of <hi>Dives</hi> and <hi>Lazarus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Midnight-Cry a Sermon. These two by <hi>John Mason</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Corbets</hi> Self-employment in Secret.</p>
            <p>A Treatise of the Day of Judgment: By Mr. <hi>Sam. Lee</hi> Minister.</p>
            <p>Husbandry Spiritualized.</p>
            <p>A Saint indeed.</p>
            <p>A Token for Mourners. All these three by Mr. <hi>John Flavel</hi> Minister of the Gospel.</p>
            <p>Satan sifting, or the Oyl of Joy for the Spirit of Sadness.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whites</hi> Little Book for Little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            <p>The rare Jewel of Christian Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with four useful Discourses, by Mr. <hi>Jer. Burroughs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Earnest Call to Family Duties being the substance of Eighteeen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons by <hi>Sam. Slater.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:206531:6"/>
            <p>Hymns for the Sacrament composed mostly out of the New Testament.</p>
            <p>Two Sermons against Quenching the Spirit. These two by <hi>Joyse Boyse</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster in <hi>Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theological Discourses and Sermons on several occasions. By <hi>John Wallis</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>The Truest and Largest account of the late Earthquake in <hi>Jamaica, June</hi> 7. 1692. from a Reverend Divine there, to his Friend in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at St. <hi>Edmunds. Bury in Suffolk</hi> at the Assizes, <hi>March</hi> 18. 1693.</p>
            <p>The best way to mend the World by perswading the Rising Generation to an Early and Serious Practice of Piety. Both by <hi>Samuel Peck</hi> Lecturer of <hi>Ipswich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Defence of Mr. <hi>Matthew Henery</hi>'s Brief Enquiry into the Nature of Schism, and the Vindication of it: With Reflections on a Pamphlet called the Review, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With a Brief Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storical account of Nonconformity from the Reformation to the present Time.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:206531:6"/>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at the Funeral of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Tho. Shewell</hi> M. A. and Minister of the Gospel in <hi>Coventry.</hi> These two last by <hi>William Tongue</hi> Minister, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Discourse concerning Old Age tending to the Instruction, Caution and comfort of Aged Persons. By <hi>Rithard Steell</hi> A. M.</p>
            <p>A Sermon at the Funeral of the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipful <hi>John Symmonds</hi> late of Great <hi>Yeldham</hi> in <hi>Essex</hi> Esq; by <hi>John Brooke</hi> M. A. and Rector there.</p>
            <p>A Vindication of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> being an Answer to five Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets; by Dr. <hi>Rule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon of the absolute necessity of Family Duties Preached to the United Parishes of St. <hi>Mary Woolnoth,</hi> and St. <hi>Mary Wool Church. Haw</hi> in <hi>Lombard-Street.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Farewel Sermon. These two by <hi>David Jones</hi> Student of <hi>Christ-Church, Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Brief Tract on the IVth, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, wherein is discovered the cause of all our Controversies about the <hi>Sabbath-Day;</hi> and the means of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling them. Recommended by the
<pb facs="tcp:206531:7"/> Reverend Dr. <hi>Bates</hi> and Mr. <hi>John How.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Convivium Caeleste:</hi> A plain and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Discourse concerning the Lords Supper, shewing at once the Nature of that Sacrament; as also the right way of preparing our selves for the receiving of it: In which are also considered those exceptions which men usually bring to excuse their not partaking of it.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached before the King and Queen at <hi>White-hall, Nov.</hi> 5. 1692. These two by <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Bishop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:206531:7"/>
            <head>Ornaments for the Daughtes of <hi>Zion.</hi> OR, The Character and Happiness of A Virtuous Woman</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>From the words of the Wise Woman In <hi>Proverbs</hi> 31. 30.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Favour is deceitful, and Beauty is vain, but A WOMAN THAT FEARETH THE LORD, She 'tis that shall be praised.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT may well be reckoned the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est <hi>Honour</hi> of that Sex, which the Holy Spirit of God has declar'd worthy of a Chast and a Kind <hi>Honour</hi> from us; <hi>That when the Fulness of Time was come, God sent forth his Son, made of a Woman.</hi> As a Woman had the <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace</hi> to <hi>go first</hi> in that horrid and woful Transgression of our first <hi>Parents,</hi> which has been the <hi>Parent</hi> of all our Misery; so a Woman had the <hi>Glory</hi> of bringing into the World that <hi>Second Adam,</hi> who
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:206531:8"/> is the <hi>Father</hi> of all our Happiness. A Woman had the <hi>Saviour</hi> of Mankind in the Circumstances of an <hi>Infant</hi> Miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously Conceiv'd within her; and of a <hi>Mary</hi> was <hi>born that Holy Thing, which is called, The Son of God.</hi> There is a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whom we do now without the mistakes, which made that expression the occasion of many Antient, and no less furious than curious Controversies, call, <hi>The Mother of Him that is God;</hi> in as much as that very <hi>Flesh</hi> which was born of her, and which the <hi>Trembling Hereticks</hi> of this Age, do not now <hi>Tremble</hi> to vilifie and nullifie with frequent Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies; I say, That Visible Tangible <hi>Flesh,</hi> is Personally United unto the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Person</hi> in the Adorable Trinity. Though we do not like the Popish Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, for this cause, imagine that Blessed Virgin to have been free from <hi>Original Sin,</hi> when she was on Earth, nor now Implore her <hi>Mediation</hi> and <hi>Intercession</hi> in Heaven for us; and though I do not think, that the Holy Ghost referr'd unto <hi>her</hi> peculiarly, as there are Expositors who think he <hi>does,</hi> when he says, <hi>The Woman that fears the Lord, she 'tis that shall be praised:</hi> Yet we may safely
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:206531:8"/> account the <hi>Female Sex</hi> herein more than a little dignified. And how should it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage all Women to seek a saving Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest in that Redeemer, who was <hi>Born of a Woman!</hi> How should all <hi>Women</hi> make their Hearts a Lodging for that Lord, who in a <hi>Woman</hi> received <hi>The Body pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for him!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second,</hi> or a priviledge not far from the <hi>Second</hi> Advancement of that Sex, may be esteemed, the Share which it has had in Writing those Oracles, which <hi>make us wise unto Salvation.</hi> As one <hi>Woman</hi> was the <hi>Mother</hi> of him who is the <hi>Essential Word</hi> of God, so divers <hi>Women</hi> have been the <hi>Writers</hi> of his <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarative Word.</hi> Though the Apostle does abundantly intimate unto us, that such <hi>Inspirations</hi> as compos'd the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> are not now to be expected, when he gives the prohibition so much Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress'd by the most Absurd Sect in our Days, <hi>That the Woman may not speak in the Church;</hi> yet our God has Employ'd many <hi>Women</hi> to <hi>Write</hi> for the <hi>Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch,</hi> and <hi>Inspir'd</hi> some of them for the Writing of the <hi>Scriptures.</hi> We have not only seen <hi>Women</hi> doing service for the <hi>Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle</hi> by such Ingenious Writings as we
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:206531:9"/> find mention'd in the Catalogues of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verovicius, Hottinger,</hi> and <hi>Voetius;</hi> or such as that most accomplish'd Lady, <hi>Anna Maria Schurman</hi> has in our Age ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dressed the World withal; for even the Books publish'd by <hi>that Sex,</hi> were enough to make a <hi>Library</hi> far from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible; nor has even the <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> part of the <hi>American</hi> Strand been without <hi>Authoresses</hi> that would challenge a Room in such a <hi>Library:</hi> They to whom the common use of <hi>Swords</hi> is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Decent nor Lawful, have made a most Laudable use of <hi>Pens;</hi> and they that might not without <hi>Sin,</hi> lead the Life which old Stories ascribe to <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zons,</hi> have with much <hi>praise</hi> done the part of <hi>Scholars</hi> in the World: But we sometimes also find a <hi>Woman</hi> among the <hi>Amanuenses</hi> or <hi>Scribes</hi> of that Spirit, who <hi>moved holy Men to write the most sure Word of Prophecy.</hi> And how much does this oblige all <hi>Women</hi> to study that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Bible, to the curious Workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship whereof, the hand of a <hi>Woman</hi> has contributed? How ready should <hi>Women</hi> be to Read the pages, upon which they may see transcribed the heavenly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries made by the God of Heaven
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:206531:9"/> to an holy <hi>Woman;</hi> rather than to mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spend their <hi>hours,</hi> and infect their <hi>hearts</hi> by the revolving of such <hi>Romances,</hi> as commonly leave a sensible Taint upon the minds of their unwary Readers?</p>
            <p>We have not only the Song of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borah,</hi> the Song of <hi>Hannah,</hi> the Song of <hi>Mary,</hi> and the Prophecy of <hi>Huldah,</hi> in this matchless Book of our God; but the Instructions of <hi>Bathshebah</hi> too, are entered in these blessed Registers. The thirty first Chapter of <hi>Proverbs</hi> contains a direction of <hi>Bathshebah</hi> to her darling <hi>Solomon. Solomon</hi> that in the fourth Chapter of this Book, records the Counsels of his <hi>Father,</hi> now in the last Chapter adds the Counsels of his <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> thereunto. So careful will wise Children be to remember the gracious Counsels of their godly Parents: We have <hi>Solomon</hi> here addressed by the name of <hi>Lemuel,</hi> which name some In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters judge to be a little and a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving imitation of his true Name; as 'tis useful with our Mothers, from the names of <hi>Edward</hi> and <hi>William,</hi> and the like, to form affectionate Appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations for us; but others waving so small a consideration, do look upon <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:206531:10"/> as one of the <hi>eight Names</hi> which the Jews do ascribe unto that <hi>Man of Name,</hi> and they tell us, that as <hi>Jedidiah</hi> proclaimed his being <hi>Beloved of the Lord, Lemuel</hi> signified his <hi>Belonging to the Lord.</hi> Some famous persons in the World, have been signaliz'd by that Character of being <hi>Mother taught;</hi> such an one was our <hi>Solomon,</hi> who had not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>Father,</hi> that lest behind him <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scendent Songs for Solomon,</hi> but also a <hi>Mother,</hi> who <hi>taught</hi> him such things as the best should not be unwilling to <hi>learn.</hi> How free, how rich is the Grace of God unto Repenting Sinners! <hi>Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shebah,</hi> after a very scandalous Fall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a very eminent Saint, yea a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetess</hi> of the Lord. Although a <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> may have been remarkable and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious for sin, yet let her endeavour to <hi>make</hi> her Peace with God: It <hi>may</hi> be made, and she may <hi>enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven,</hi> before others that have not had such <hi>wounds</hi> upon them.</p>
            <p>'Tis evident, that the <hi>nine</hi> first verses of the Chapter, are spent in Reciting the most prudent and winning <hi>Lessons</hi> of <hi>Bathshebah</hi> to her <hi>Solomon.</hi> But it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that the rest of the Chapter is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:206531:10"/> only <hi>Solomons</hi> Reciprocation in the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of <hi>Bathshebah.</hi> It is indeed a most lovely thing to see such Correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies of <hi>Desert</hi> and <hi>Duty,</hi> as make Children to count their <hi>Mothers</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of their honour: Noble Romans have sometimes made Florid Speeches at the Funerals of their <hi>Mothers,</hi> and professed, <hi>That they had never in their Lives been reconciled unto them,</hi> inasmuch as (they meant) they had never <hi>fallen out:</hi> It is the happiness of a <hi>Mother</hi> sometimes to have such Sons as <hi>Nazien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen</hi> and <hi>Austin</hi> were unto theirs, whose Names are by their means forever Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated: although for the most part we see in mens Readiness to <hi>Slight</hi> their <hi>Mothers,</hi> the Reason why the <hi>Mother</hi> is put first in that Charge of our God. <hi>Ye shall fear every man his Mother, and his Father.</hi> It is the Opinion of others, That the Conclusion of the Chapter, is also the Composure of <hi>Bathshebah;</hi> and that which confirms them in this Opinion is, The Skill in <hi>Houshold Affairs</hi> here manifested, which Carries a Little of a <hi>Female Aspect</hi> with it. However it be, we have here the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of, <hi>A Virtuous Woman,</hi> in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:206531:11"/> twenty two Verses, according to the Number and Order of the Letters, in the Hebrew Alphabet; Every letter in due sequence beginning a several Verse. 'Tis reported, that <hi>Children</hi> among the <hi>Jews</hi> of old Learning to <hi>Write,</hi> had their <hi>Copies</hi> usually given them from those Portions of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which were drawn up with such an <hi>Alphabet</hi> of the Hebrew Letters in them; whether that were so, or no, I am sure that <hi>Women</hi> among the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> in our Days, Learning to <hi>Live,</hi> cannot easily find better <hi>Copies</hi> to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, than those which are in our Context here set before them. It were to be wished, That the <hi>Sex</hi> which so often looks into the <hi>Glass,</hi> would sometimes cast an eye upon this part of that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <hi>Word,</hi> which is compar'd unto a Divine <hi>Glass;</hi> that they may see whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have the <hi>Features,</hi> or <hi>Habits</hi> of <hi>The Virtuous Woman,</hi> on them. And I pray, let no <hi>Woman</hi> count her self so great a <hi>Lady</hi> as to put in her Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, against that Stroke in the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> here; <hi>She seeks Wooll and Flax, and Works willingly with her Hands,</hi> till she has procured
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:206531:11"/> the Alteration of the English Laws, wherein, <hi>Spinster,</hi> is a Term given to Women of the greatest Quality. When a Gentlewoman of Extraordinary Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was presented before the first King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> his first Question to her, was, <hi>Madam, Can you Spin?</hi> And several of the most Renowned Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours▪ have not only Obliged their Daughters to <hi>Spin,</hi> but also Wore such Garments as those Princely Hands had prepared for them. The <hi>Cards</hi> at which many Gentlewoman <hi>Play wickedly with their Hands,</hi> are far more Debasing, than those <hi>Cards</hi> which fit the Wooll for the Wheel: and the <hi>Distaff</hi> is an Instrument of better Quality than the <hi>Dice.</hi> The Famous Queen <hi>Katharine,</hi> when persons of high Rank were sent unto her with a Message from King <hi>Henry,</hi> counted it no Disgrace to be found with a Skein of Red Silk about her Neck, at Work, with a <hi>Maid of Honour</hi> by her side. She that hath <hi>Bought a Field</hi> has not thereby Bought a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lease from <hi>Domestick Businesses;</hi> the <hi>Hands</hi> which Carve at the most Noble Tables, may be <hi>Laid unto the Spindle,</hi> without
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:206531:12"/> being Dishonourably Blistered or Dirt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there.</p>
            <p>'Tis a foolish Custom which the Jews have in Reading <hi>Solomons</hi> Book of <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastes;</hi> that they Print the <hi>Last Verse but One,</hi> of it, over again in the Close of all, because they would have the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance and Impression of <hi>that Verse</hi> to be Stronger upon them, than that of the terrible verse which follows it. But having laid before you the Descrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>A Virtuous Woman,</hi> which closes up <hi>Solomons</hi> Book of <hi>Proverbs;</hi> I must upon another Account Print, and ask the Daughters of our Common Mother to Read the <hi>last verse but one,</hi> over again; 'tis this.</p>
            <q>FAVOƲR is Deceitful, and Beauty is Vain; but a Woman, that Fears the Lord, She 'tis that shall be Praised.</q>
            <p>The Words are, as one says of them, <hi>A Royal Garland set on the Head of a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Woman by the Hand of God.</hi> Some Interpreters do so <hi>Allegorize</hi> these Words, that they make this <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> to be the <hi>Church</hi> of God. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, there are more <hi>Women</hi> than <hi>Men,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:206531:12"/> in the Church; and the more <hi>Virtuous</hi> they prove, the more Worthy will the Church be, to be figured by, <hi>A Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that Fears the Lord.</hi> Some Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters again, do so <hi>Sublimate</hi> the words, that they understand every Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Pious, Devout <hi>Soul</hi> by this <hi>Virtuous Woman.</hi> And it were well, if <hi>Women</hi> were generally so <hi>Virtuous,</hi> as that they might worthily impart unto every God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Soul, the Denomination of, <hi>A Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that Fears the Lord.</hi> Other Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters do suppose <hi>Virtue</hi> it self to be meant by the <hi>Virtuous Woman.</hi> But, we should be sorry, if a <hi>Virtuous Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> prove so rare a thing, as to afford a stile for a <hi>Parable</hi> rather than an <hi>Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> I confess, <hi>Virtue</hi> it self, and the <hi>Names</hi> of all Particular <hi>Virtues,</hi> are Grammatically of the <hi>Female Gender;</hi> and that the <hi>Things</hi> may Theologically abound in that <hi>Gender,</hi> is what we may thence take occasion to be wishing for. But after all, 'Tis a Real, Proper, Gracious <hi>Woman,</hi> that has her <hi>Character</hi> and <hi>Blessedness</hi> in these words Exhibited unto us.—</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:206531:13"/>
            <p>The first thing with which we are here treated is,</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I. THE CHARACTER <hi>of</hi> a <hi>Virtuous Woman.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And this Character is both <hi>Negatively</hi> and <hi>Positively</hi> offered. Negatively, 'Tis not a <hi>Deceitful Favour,</hi> or, a <hi>Vain Beauty</hi> that sets her off; Women that have none but those things to Value themselves upon, are driven out from <hi>The Temple of Honour,</hi> here. But, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitively, 'Tis the <hi>Fear of the Lord</hi> that is her Commendation. 'Tis implied, not only that <hi>Favour</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> are poor things compar'd with the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> but also that they who have the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> will not Value themselves upon their <hi>Favour</hi> and <hi>Beauty.</hi> Yea, that there is a <hi>Favour</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site, Contrary, Destructive to the <hi>Fear of God.</hi> We may reflect upon the whole, in these Conclusions.</p>
               <div n="1" type="conclusion">
                  <head>Conclusion. 1.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> counts the best Female <hi>Favour</hi> to be <hi>Deceitful,</hi> the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:206531:13"/> best Female <hi>Beauty</hi> to be <hi>Vain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>Favour</hi> is meant, a Comely Presence, an Handsome Carriage, a Decent Gesture, a ready Wit agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably expressing it self, with all other Graceful Motions, and whatsoever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures <hi>Favour</hi> for a Woman among her Neighbours. The <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> is willing to have this <hi>Favour,</hi> so far as is consistent with <hi>Virtue;</hi> She counts it a <hi>Favour</hi> of God for one to be graced with it; But still she looks upon it as a <hi>Deceitful</hi> thing. She is careful, that She do not hereby <hi>Deceive</hi> her self into proud Imaginations, and into an Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, <hi>Conceited</hi> of her self, or <hi>Contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous</hi> towards others. Careful She like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise is, lest hereby She <hi>Decieve</hi> Unwary men, <hi>into</hi> those Amours which bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing looks and smiles do often betray the Children of men, especially those that are <hi>but</hi> Children of men, into.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Beauty</hi> is meant, a good Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Symmetry of the parts, and a skin well Varnished, or that which <hi>Chrysostom</hi> calls, <hi>A good mixture of Blood and Flegm shining through a good Skin;</hi> With all that Harmonious Air of the Countenance, which recommends it
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:206531:14"/> self, as a <hi>Beauty</hi> to the Eye of the Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctator. The <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful for this <hi>Beauty,</hi> when the God of Nature has bestow'd any of it on her; and yet she counts it no <hi>Virtue</hi> for her to be very sensible of her being illustrated with such a <hi>Beauty.</hi> But still she looks upon it as a <hi>Vain</hi> thing. She reckons it so <hi>Vain,</hi> that she has no Assurance for the continuance of it; but that it is <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris &amp; Morbi Ludibrium,</hi> as one of the Antients has descanted on it; a thing neither <hi>Age-proof,</hi> nor <hi>Ague-proof.</hi> She sees that <hi>Vanity</hi> in it, which is upon the quickly Withering <hi>Roses</hi> and <hi>Lillies</hi> of the Field: Such a <hi>Vanity</hi> as that <hi>Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beds</hi> or <hi>Sun beams,</hi> or a thousand Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sualties may soon destroy that Idol of the <hi>Amorites.</hi> And upon these thoughts, a <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> takes heed of becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so <hi>Deceitful</hi> and <hi>Vain,</hi> as many Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are tempted by their <hi>Favour</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> to become.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="conclusion">
                  <head>Conclusion 2.</head>
                  <p>There is a <hi>Favour</hi> so particularly <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful,</hi> and a <hi>Beauty</hi> so remarkably <hi>Vain,</hi> as that a <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> would be loth to be <hi>Deformed</hi> with it.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:206531:14"/>
                  <p>The <hi>Favour</hi> whereat a <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> has a particular Distast, is that which <hi>promiscuous Dancing</hi> is applauded for. The exercise of <hi>promiscuous Dancing</hi> is that which pretends to be a piece of Breeding which demands the <hi>Favour</hi> of Woman-kind; but a <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> esteems them <hi>deceived</hi> who count it so; nor will she affect such an Exercise. <hi>Job</hi> recounts it as part of the Breeding which the Ungodly bestow upon their Children, in <hi>Chap. 21. 11. Their Children Dance.</hi> Now the <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> is not fond of being that way employ'd. We read the Haughty Daughters of <hi>Zion</hi> described and threatned in <hi>Isa.</hi> 3. 16. as <hi>walking and min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing as they go.</hi> Very Renowned Expositors conceive that Scripture to refer unto the Haughty Carriages learned in the <hi>Dancing School.</hi> The Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 13. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns <hi>Rioting;</hi> and the Apostle <hi>Peter,</hi> in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 3. condemns <hi>Revelling</hi> Now the most Learned Criticks in the Greek Tongue, judge <hi>Dancing</hi> to be the thing intended in the word there used by those Apostles. Moreover, the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Assembly of Divines, in their Larger Catechism, very justly mention
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:206531:15"/>
                     <hi>Dancings</hi> among the things forbidden in the Seventh Commandment of our God. Nor does the <hi>Levity</hi> of <hi>Dancings</hi> wherein persons leap and fling about so like <hi>Bedlams,</hi> that the wisest Men have call'd it, <hi>A Regular Madness,</hi> now agree well with the <hi>Gravity,</hi> which Holiness is to be accompanied withal. Such things as these are enough to make a <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> to discard such Dancings from among <hi>the things of good report;</hi> and leave them either to the Pagans, whose manner 'twas to <hi>Dance</hi> in the Worship of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> or to the Monkeys, whom of old they brought forth to <hi>Dance</hi> at the Festival of <hi>Diana.</hi> Some of the more sober Papists have not stuck to say, <hi>The Dancer breaks the Covenant of God, made in Baptism; he promised to renounce the Devil, and his Pomps: But when he enters into a Dance, he goes in the Pompous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of the Devil.</hi> They are not a few silly scrupulous Precisians, by whom these <hi>Dancings</hi> have been stigmatized. In the Primitive Times, more than one or two of the <hi>Fathers</hi> thundred against them as a <hi>Diabolical practice;</hi> and whole <hi>Synods</hi> did prohibit the usage of them, even at Weddings as well as at other
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:206531:15"/> Seasons. Nor have Reforming <hi>Synods</hi> of later days in <hi>France, Holland, Poland,</hi> forborn to brandish the Sword of <hi>Church-Discipline,</hi> and provide <hi>Censures</hi> for any <hi>Dancers</hi> that might be found among their Communicants. <hi>Austin</hi> says, <hi>The miserable Dancer knows not, that as many paces as he makes in Dancing, so many steps he makes to Hell.</hi> And the blessed old <hi>Waldenses</hi> testified, <hi>In a Dance one breaks all the Ten Commandments of God.</hi> The most Eminent Reformers above an hundred years ago, concurred in witnessing against these <hi>Dances,</hi> as an <hi>Ʋnlawful Recreation;</hi> and among the English <hi>Divines,</hi> yea among the English <hi>Bishops,</hi> they have been decry'd by a <hi>Cloud of Witnesses;</hi> they have branded our <hi>Dancers</hi> as the <hi>Capering Goats,</hi> that will not be found among the <hi>Sheep</hi> in the Day of the Lord. Shall we say it? Even the Antient <hi>Romans,</hi> although they were Heathens, yet reputed skill in Dancing an Infamous thing. <hi>Scipio</hi> call'd a Dance, <hi>Impudent; Salust</hi> call'd a Dance, <hi>Dishonest;</hi> and they cited it as a Note of Infamy. <hi>Tully</hi> could say, <hi>A Dancer is doubtless either drunk or mad;</hi> and he argued against some, that they
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:206531:16"/> must needs be <hi>Vicious,</hi> inasmuch as they were <hi>Dancers;</hi> nor did <hi>Seneca</hi> think it any other than a matter of bitter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, <hi>That there were Dancing-Schools tolerated in the City.</hi> These are consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations enough to deter a <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> from the <hi>Dances,</hi> which are now become so acceptable to <hi>This Adulterous Generation.</hi> Pardon me this freedom; I had been <hi>worse than an Infidel,</hi> if I had not used it; for I remember <hi>Plutarch</hi> himself enumerating the Qualifications of a <hi>Virtuous Woman;</hi> gives this for one, <hi>She must not be a Dancer.</hi> The Daughter of <hi>Herodias</hi> has been so stigmatized, that a <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> will not be for <hi>Dancing</hi> after her.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Beauty</hi> whereof a <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> hath a remarkable dislike, is that which hath <hi>Artificial Painting</hi> in it. The usage of <hi>Artificial Painting</hi> is practised by many Women, who think thereby to be valued for a <hi>Beauty,</hi> which they are not really the owners of: But a <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> will not be guilty of such a <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> There is a wicked Book that pleads for this ungodly practice; but that good Lady uttered the Language of a <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> upon reading such a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:206531:16"/> Book, <hi>O Lord, I thank thee, that thou gavest me not Wit enough to write such a Book, u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>less withal thou hadst given me Grace enough not to write it.</hi> Although it be not unlawful for a Person transi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to preserve or to restore her Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Complexion</hi> by convenient Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, when she is in any special danger of losing it; yet for a Person to <hi>Paint</hi> her self, that she may make some osten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>station of a Complexion which God has not made her the owner of, is a thing that has heard ill among the most godly Christians; nor will a <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> easily be reconcil'd unto it; lest when the Saints Rise as <hi>Tertullian</hi> wished <hi>he</hi> might at the Resurrection of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, <hi>To see whether the Angels are then carrying any Painted Ladies in their Arms to meet the Lord Jesus Christ with Joy;</hi> there will be no such sight then to be met withal. The wicked <hi>Harlots</hi> of old Painted their <hi>Eyes,</hi> as 'tis said in <hi>Ezek. 33. 40. Thou paintest thy Eyes;</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand it of their <hi>Eye-brows</hi> and <hi>Eye lids,</hi> which they ting'd with a preparation of <hi>Antimony</hi> to <hi>blacken</hi> them, and <hi>beautifie</hi> 'em. This was accounted an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Comliness; and therefore about
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:206531:17"/> the <hi>Harlot</hi> is the Young Man advised in <hi>Prov. 6. 25. Let her not take thee with her Eye-lids.</hi> Of such Eyes 'twas that <hi>Cyprian</hi> said, <hi>These are not Eyes with which our God is to be look'd unto!</hi> And <hi>Jerom</hi> reckons 'em among scandalous <hi>Harlotries.</hi> Now this is one Argument which the <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> has against the <hi>Painting</hi> of her Face in any part of it; <hi>It is the Guise of an Harlot.</hi> An <hi>Adulterate</hi> Complexion is but agreeable to an <hi>Adulterous</hi> Condition. A <hi>Painted Face</hi> is but a <hi>Painted Sign</hi> hung out for advice to Strangers, that they shall find Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment there. 'Tis often the <hi>VVhores Forehead</hi> which admits <hi>Paint</hi> upon it. 'Tis well if you do not find a <hi>Snake</hi> where you see a <hi>Painted Skin.</hi> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, our <hi>Face</hi> is a Seat which has much of the Divine <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>VVisdom</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in it; and it is a vile Affront unto God, for a Woman to <hi>Deface</hi> the Workmanship of the Almighty there; by such an <hi>Inversion,</hi> as the Hebrew word for this <hi>Painting</hi> signifies. Now, the <hi>Paint</hi> which is laid upon it, not only dis-figures the Face for the present, but also do's corrupt it and corrode it, and poison it, and hasten wrinkles and ruines there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:206531:17"/> it will <hi>Rent the Face,</hi> as the Scripture speaks of it; and I am sure, it should <hi>Rent the Heart,</hi> of them that use it. Besides, Our Lord Rebuked it, as a base <hi>Hypocrisie</hi> for Persons to <hi>alter their Faces</hi> that they might appear to be <hi>Fasting,</hi> when they were so indeed; how much more basely Hypocritical is it, for Persons to <hi>alter their Faces</hi> that they might appear to be <hi>Comely</hi> when indeed they are not so? There is no <hi>Sincerity</hi> in these <hi>Butterflies.</hi> It is a <hi>Cheat</hi> which there is no enduring of. The more Moral Heathen shew'd a great Indignation at it; and shall we think a <hi>Vertuous Woman</hi> can allow of it? And alas, what a World of Precious Time, is thus thrown away, by poor Creatures, who are so taken up with <hi>Painting</hi> of the <hi>Sepulchres</hi> in which their <hi>Souls</hi> lye <hi>Dead,</hi> as that they do little or nothing for the Beautifying of those <hi>Black,</hi> Forlorn, Forsaken Souls? The sin committed in <hi>Paintings</hi> we must sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose committed in <hi>Patches</hi> too. When the Face is <hi>Patched</hi> the Heart is <hi>Rotten,</hi> the Heart has more <hi>Black Spots</hi> than the Face upon it. Some unhappy Ladies by the Just Judgment of God, have
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:206531:18"/> brought forth Children with Natural <hi>Patches</hi> on: so has Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> been offended at them. The Antients tell us, that the Devil was the Inventor of this <hi>Hellish Art;</hi> and it can be nothing but either <hi>Lust</hi> or <hi>Pride</hi> (both Bras of the <hi>Devil!</hi>) that shall dispose any to the using of it. If they that <hi>Please men,</hi> much more, I am sure they that thus <hi>Cheat men,</hi> cannot be <hi>The Servants of Christ; Tertullian</hi> well calls them, <hi>The Handmaids of the Devil;</hi> nor when they <hi>Paint their Bodies</hi> do they <hi>Glorifie the Lord with their Bodies.</hi> A <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> would be loth to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low no better Patterns than <hi>Jezebel</hi> or <hi>Maximilla,</hi> both of which Woful Creatures have this related of them, <hi>That they Paint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d their Faces.</hi> For <hi>such</hi> would She leave these foul <hi>Paintings;</hi> and now the old <hi>Picts</hi> are dead, She would not help to Revive that <hi>Pagan</hi> Generation or make her self a Sister to the <hi>Squaws</hi> in the Thickets of <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica.</hi> Nor would She be in the way of such Thunder-bolts, as Dr. <hi>Hall</hi> in Imitation of the blessed Ancients once darted against such Transgressors, <hi>Hear this, ye Plaister-faced</hi> Jezabels; <hi>if you will not leave your Dawbings and your High
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:206531:18"/> Washes, God will one Day wash them off with Fire and Brimstone!</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="conclusion">
                  <head>Conclusion. 3.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Fear of God</hi> is that which the Heart of a <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> is under the Power of. The <hi>Female Sex</hi> is naturally the <hi>Fearful Sex;</hi> but the <hi>Fear of God</hi> is that which Exceeds (and sometimes Extinguishes) all other <hi>Fears</hi> in the <hi>Virtuous Woman.</hi> To state this matter aright, we are to know, That the <hi>Fear of God</hi> is an <hi>Old</hi> Testament Expression, as the <hi>Love of God</hi> is a <hi>New</hi> Testament one, for all true <hi>Religion</hi> whatsoever. It may then be said of a <hi>Virtuous Woman,</hi> That she is a <hi>Religious Woman;</hi> She has <hi>Bound</hi> her self <hi>again</hi> to that God, whom She had by the Sin and Fall of her <hi>First Mother</hi> departed from; She has a <hi>Love</hi> which does not cast <hi>out the Fear</hi> that is no <hi>Fault,</hi> but confirm and settle her in that <hi>Fear</hi> of God; That all kind of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> is prevailing in her Disposition; That <hi>Sobriety,</hi> and <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness,</hi> and <hi>Godliness</hi> are Visible in her whole Behaviour; and, that She does <hi>Justice,</hi> loves <hi>Mercy,</hi> and walks
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:206531:19"/>
                     <hi>Humbly</hi> with her God. But that we may speak somewhat more particularly.</p>
                  <p>First, A <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> has <hi>Awful</hi> as well as <hi>Real</hi> Apprehensions, <hi>That there is a God.</hi> When <hi>Jacob</hi> of old per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the <hi>Presence</hi> of God, it is said, in Gen. 28. 17. <hi>He was Afraid.</hi> The Vertuous Woman in like manner Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves the <hi>Essence</hi> of God; and that thought, <hi>God is,</hi> it raises a Sacred <hi>Fear</hi> of Him in her humble and moved Soul. She sees the <hi>Being</hi> of a God prov'd from the Works of <hi>Creation:</hi> even as he that made the Image of <hi>Minerva</hi> ingraved his own Name upon it so, that it could not be taken out without breaking all to pieces. The whole World is a <hi>Book,</hi> and all Creatures are the <hi>Letters</hi> in it, whereby She Spells out the Existence of a GOD. Even the <hi>Dumb,</hi> the <hi>Mute</hi> Creatures do loudly <hi>speak</hi> this Truth unto her she Considers, That the World had a <hi>Beginning;</hi> inasmuch as 'tis <hi>Older</hi> and <hi>Changing</hi> every Day: And that it could not have its <hi>Beginning</hi> from it self; inasmuch as <hi>Nothing</hi> would then be the cause of <hi>Something.</hi> So, She sees, there is a GOD; and She sees the <hi>Wisdom</hi> of a GOD, the <hi>Power</hi> of a GOD, the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:206531:19"/>
                     <hi>Goodness</hi> of a GOD, throughout the Universe. She sees likewise the <hi>Being</hi> of GOD plain in the Works of <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence;</hi> which preserves all things in a most Excellent <hi>Order,</hi> Subordinate and Subservient unto a Glorious End. She sees the World like a Vast <hi>Army</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed of Quarrelsome, Contentious, Contrary things, and yet holding well together; whereupon she concludes, <hi>There is a GOD who is the Wise General over all.</hi> She considers the extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Occurrences in the World; and when She sees <hi>Prophecies</hi> that exactly foretell what comes to pass many Ages after; When she sees <hi>Miracles,</hi> that give Check to the Common Course and Road of Nature; When She sees <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> extraordinarily Answered, Good Men extraordinarily <hi>Rewarded,</hi> Ill men Extraordinarily <hi>Punished,</hi> She cries out, <hi>The Finger of a GOD is here!</hi> She finds her self born with a Notion of a GOD, wherein she has not been by any <hi>Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> or <hi>Policy</hi> of others Impos'd upon; and She graciously Cherishes that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. All Ancient Histories hardly mention above Twenty <hi>Profest Atheists;</hi> and of those that were counted <hi>such,</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:206531:20"/> there never was one, without frequent and vehement suspitions of a GOD. But all Tendencies to <hi>Atheism</hi> are most abominable to the Soul of a Virtuous Woman. She is not such a <hi>Fool,</hi> as to <hi>say</hi> with her <hi>Mouth,</hi> or to <hi>Think</hi> with <hi>her Heart,</hi> or to <hi>say in her Heart,</hi> and Wish, <hi>There is no God.</hi> The Being of a GOD is at once the <hi>Fear,</hi> and yet the <hi>Wish</hi> of her Godly Soul. If any De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signing, Debauched <hi>Atheist,</hi> go to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinuate unto her; That the Notion of GOD, and HEAVEN, and HELL, and an Immortal SOUL, is but a Trick of some cunning Divines. her Answer is with an Indignation, Speedy and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry like a Flash of Lightning, <hi>Satan, be gone!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Next; A <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> has a most <hi>Reverent</hi> Respect and Regard unto all that has the <hi>Name</hi> of God upon it. They that have the <hi>Fear of God</hi> in them, are by Him so stiled, in Mal. 4. 2. <hi>You that Fear my Name.</hi> The <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is all that, whereby He makes Himself Known unto us; and a Virtuous Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man will not Irreverently Use any such Thing, lest She should be <hi>held not Guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less before the Lord.</hi> She will not utter
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:206531:20"/> the <hi>Titles</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in any Frothy and Foolish manner; nor will she have a low opinion of His <hi>Attributes;</hi> nor will she with a Carnal Spirit come unto his <hi>Ordinances.</hi> Yea, so far she is from Affronting the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>God</hi> her self, that although she should be <hi>Dressed</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so Fine, yet if she Chance to hear the <hi>Name</hi> of God Blasphemed, she can scarce forbear the <hi>Rending</hi> of her <hi>Clothes,</hi> as the Usage of the Jews was on such a Provocation; be sure, it causes the <hi>Reading</hi> of her <hi>Heart.</hi> Especially, the <hi>Word</hi> of God, is what she <hi>Fears</hi> to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spise or Controul, or Disobey; it may be said of her, <hi>She Fears the Commandment;</hi> it may be said by her, <hi>My Heart stands in Fear of thy Word.</hi> Of the <hi>Precepts</hi> in that Word, it is then, <hi>Fear, Oh let me not break them!</hi> Of the <hi>Promises</hi> there, 'tis her <hi>Fear, Oh let me not fall Short of them!</hi> Of the <hi>Menaces</hi> there, 'tis her <hi>Fear, Oh let them never take hold of me!</hi> And at the same time, the Virtuous Woman is very much Concerned, That the <hi>Name</hi> of God may be duely honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the World. <hi>Sanctify'd be thy Name</hi> is the first Petition of her Soul unto her Lord. She would not for the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:206531:21"/> most Massy Wedges of Gold, ever do any thing, that may bring Reproach to the dear <hi>Name</hi> of God; but she Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, Contrives, Labours to Advance that Blessed <hi>Name</hi> as far as ever she can; <hi>Oh</hi> (she thinks) <hi>How may the Name of my Good God, be by my means Exalted in the World!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly; A <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> is very circumspect and solicitous to <hi>avoid</hi> what the God of Heaven may be <hi>offended</hi> at. The Wise-man takes notice of this, as one Ingredient in the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> Prov. 16. 6. <hi>By the fear of the Lord men depart from evil.</hi> And it is accordingly the desire of the Virtuous Woman, to shun all that <hi>Evil</hi> which God may be displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed at. She flies from every <hi>Known Sin,</hi> as from a direful Serpent, or from a deadly Poison; because that she sees it offensive unto that God, who <hi>is of purer Eyes than to behold evil, and cannot look upon iniquity.</hi> What we read of <hi>Job,</hi> is likewise to be said of her, <hi>She is a perfect woman, one that fears God, and eschews evil.</hi> She cannot bear the thought of incurring the Anger of that <hi>God,</hi> who <hi>Overturns the Mountains in his Anger;</hi> and she trembles before that <hi>God,</hi> at
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:206531:21"/> whose Voice even the <hi>Pillars of Heaven do tremble.</hi> She had rather undergo any miseries, than incur the intollerable and interminable Torments which the Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent God has to inflict upon them that <hi>provoke him to Jealousie;</hi> and upon that account she is <hi>fearful</hi> of every thing that may be provoking to her Holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. When she over-hears the Lord, saying, <hi>Oh do not the Abominable things that my Soul hates,</hi> her answer is in words like those that <hi>Joseph</hi> had unto his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, <hi>Oh I dare not, cannot commit such things, for I fear God!</hi> If other Women will speak vainly, dress proudly, live lewdly, she can say as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did of old, <hi>But so do not I because I have the Fear of God!</hi> The Exquisite Pen of a <hi>Dutch</hi> Lady hath Celebrated the <hi>Zeal</hi> of a <hi>Scotch</hi> Woman, who for her <hi>Zeal</hi> having her Leg tortured in that cruel Horrid Engine call'd <hi>the Boot,</hi> bravely said, <hi>My God I bless thee that thou hast given me a Leg to be thus used for thee!</hi> Thus would this Person rather have all her <hi>Bones broken,</hi> than to sin so against God, that like <hi>David</hi> she must cry out of, <hi>Broken Bones.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:206531:22"/>
                  <p>Fouthly, A <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> Labours to <hi>Please</hi> and <hi>Serve</hi> the great God, with the greatest of her cares. The <hi>Fear</hi> of God, is thus described by the Apostle, in <hi>Heb. 12. 28. Let us Serve God Accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with Reverence and Godly Fear.</hi> And nothing is more <hi>Acceptable</hi> to the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Woman, than that she may <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptably Serve</hi> her God. Let her be of never so <hi>High</hi> Rank, she thinks it no stoop for her, to be a <hi>Servant</hi> of that Lord, who has all the Angels in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for his <hi>Ministers;</hi> nor do's her Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion vary from that of those Apostles who chose, to be call'd, <hi>The Servants of Jesus Christ,</hi> when they might have been called, <hi>His Kinsmen;</hi> or of those Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, who valued it as one of their Prerogatives, to subscribe themselves, <hi>The Vassals of the Lord Jesus Christ!</hi> Let her be of never so <hi>Low</hi> Rank, She will not stoop to be a <hi>Servant</hi> of the World, or of the Flesh, or of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel; nor can she brook that the Curse of so being <hi>A Servant of Servants,</hi> ever should come upon her. When she con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templates that Lord, who is <hi>A greater than Solomon,</hi> she cries out, <hi>Happy are thy Servants; Oh that I might be one of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:206531:22"/> them!</hi> And she would always be doing the will of God, in such a manner, as may be pleasing to Him. We read of One, <hi>He had this Testimony, that He pleased God.</hi> Now, That is the Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial to be given of the Virtuous Woman; She aspires after the Imitation of the Lord Jesus, in, <hi>Doing always the things that please the Father.</hi> It is the Name of a good man, <hi>The man that pleaseth God;</hi> and whatever Change the Name of this Woman may undergo, still she keeps that Name, <hi>The Woman that pleaseth God.</hi> How so? Even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that she do's all she can in and for the <hi>Service</hi> of God; and she would not leave Room for that Expostulation of the Lord, <hi>If I be a Master, where is my Fear?</hi> No, as often as she says, <hi>Our Father,</hi> so often do's her Heart within her say, <hi>Our Master is in Heaven!</hi> We read in the Bible, concerning, <hi>certain Women that Ministred unto Jesus;</hi> and this Woman is Ambitious to be of that Blessed Company.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, A <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> does attend the <hi>Worship</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> with an Unwearied and Exemplary Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. The <hi>Proselytes,</hi> that of old were
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:206531:23"/> brought unto the <hi>Worship</hi> of the True <hi>God,</hi> are thus distinguished, in Psal. 115. 11. <hi>Ye that Fear the Lord.</hi> And the Virtuous Woman accordingly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presses her <hi>Fear</hi> of God. by <hi>Worshiping</hi> of Him that is <hi>Worthy to be Feared.</hi> It may with only the necessary Variation, be said of her, as it was of <hi>Cornelius</hi> long ago, <hi>She is a Devout Woman, and one that Fears God, and Prays to God, always.</hi> As the Almighty God was called, <hi>The Fear of Isaac;</hi> because He was <hi>Worshiped</hi> by that Renowned man; so may He be called, <hi>The Fear of the Virtuous Woman;</hi> because this Woman will observe all the parts of that <hi>Worship</hi> which is due unto the Lord. There is the <hi>Natural Worship</hi> of God, whereto she is no less Piously <hi>Affected,</hi> than Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly Accustomed. She is a <hi>Woman</hi> full of <hi>Prayer,</hi> and Perhaps it may be said concerning every Room of her House, <hi>She has Perfum'd it with her Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Prayer</hi> is what she will be <hi>Early</hi> as well as often at; and she is every Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Jealous, lest like <hi>Origen,</hi> she give the Devil an advantage by omitting of it. She makes not her <hi>Closet</hi> a place for meer Trifles and Pictures, but for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:206531:23"/>
                     <hi>Prayers</hi> with Devoutest <hi>Meditations.</hi> She retires into her <hi>Closet</hi> every Day, that she may there have a Visit from the Eternal <hi>Bridegroom</hi> of her Soul; and whatever Exercises may be at any time upon her mind, She does as <hi>Hannah</hi> did; <hi>She Pours out her Soul unto the Lord, that she may be no more sad.</hi> Yea, she is not unacquainted with solemn <hi>Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and solemn <hi>Thanksgivings,</hi> upon the Just Occasions of them. She is a Woman whom <hi>Scriptures</hi> and <hi>Sermons</hi> are very dear unto: and it is not every Trifle (as the want of a Garment, or a dread of the Weather) that she will make her excuse for her Absence from the <hi>means of Grace.</hi> How fain would she be with <hi>Mary,</hi> always hearing the sweet Admonitions of her Lord, about, <hi>The One Thing Needful,</hi> and <hi>The Good part which cannot be taken way!</hi> The <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> she calls <hi>Her Delight;</hi> nor will she wast the Sacred hours of it, in the <hi>Naughty Superfluities</hi> of Diet and Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but be as often as well she can, in the Congregation of, <hi>The People of God;</hi> and there, as her <hi>Voice</hi> makes a sound that shall be no <hi>Base,</hi> for the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick of the Publick <hi>Psalms,</hi> thus her
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:206531:24"/>
                     <hi>Heart</hi> is an <hi>Altar</hi> from whence, during the whole Solemnity, there ascend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, <hi>The Sacrifices which He desires.</hi> There is likewise, the <hi>Appointed Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship</hi> of God, whereto she counts her self most Indispensably Obliged. She can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bear to be shut out from the <hi>Church</hi> of God, any more than <hi>Miriam</hi> from the <hi>Camp</hi> of old; but whatever <hi>Longings</hi> ever may disturb her, she never has any more Craving and Raging ones than this, <hi>Oh God, Thou art my God, my Soul Thirsteth for thee, my Flesh Longeth for thee, to see thy Power and thy Glory in the Sanctuary!</hi> Indeed among the <hi>Turks</hi> the <hi>Women</hi> do never go to Church; but <hi>Christian Women</hi> would count it <hi>Hell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth</hi> to be so debarr'd. She is De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous to <hi>Eat</hi> and to <hi>Drink,</hi> where she may not <hi>Speak;</hi> and having been <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized,</hi> she is not satisfied until she come to <hi>Eat</hi> among the <hi>Friends,</hi> to <hi>Drink</hi> among the <hi>Beloved,</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ. She will not make part of that <hi>Ʋnworthy Croud,</hi> which throng out of Doors, when the <hi>Supper</hi> of the Lord is going to be administred, as if they were Frighted at it; or had cause to say, <hi>The Table of the Lord is Polluted.</hi> She dares
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:206531:24"/> not indeed come without a <hi>Wedding Garment,</hi> but she will not stay away like those, whose only Real Apology can be, <hi>They are loth to be at the Pains of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Garment on.</hi> Although she some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times counts her self as a <hi>Dog,</hi> yet like that <hi>Syrophenician</hi> Woman, she will ask for some <hi>Crumbs from the Table of the Lord.</hi> Having had her Soul <hi>Purify'd</hi> by <hi>Regeneration,</hi> she brings her <hi>Offerings</hi> to the <hi>Tabernacle.</hi> She presents unto the Church (if it be asked for) a sensible Account, like another <hi>Lydia,</hi> of some never to be forgotten Things which <hi>God has done for her Soul;</hi> or at least, she makes the Church to understand, like <hi>Ruth</hi> of old, <hi>That she would come to Rest under the Wings of the God of Israel.</hi> Nor would she let the <hi>Buffetings</hi> of the Devil altogether discourage her from joining her self to some Holy Society of Believers, where she may have her <hi>Soul bound up in the bundle of Life.</hi> She was a Noble Woman of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> that left her Friends, her House, her Plate, and all, and because the Gates of the City were Guarded, Crept through the Common Sewer, that she might Enjoy the <hi>Institutions</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:206531:25"/> at another place where they might be had. Such is the esteem which a <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Woman</hi> has for the <hi>Institutions</hi> of our Lord, she can say, <hi>Lord, I have loved the place where thy Honour dwells!</hi> and when she can't <hi>Go,</hi> yet she'll <hi>Creep</hi> to, <hi>The Habitation of His House.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the <hi>Virtuous Woman!</hi> It was very cruelly spoken by those two very Ancient Poets; the first of which usually [in his Comedies] represented <hi>Women</hi> as <hi>very bad;</hi> but the latter usually repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented them, <hi>very good;</hi> saying, <hi>The first represented what they are, the latter what they should be.</hi> I hope I have in this Discourse represented, not only, what <hi>all</hi> Women <hi>should be,</hi> but also, what <hi>very many</hi> of them <hi>Are.</hi> And for <hi>their</hi> Encouragement, we will now pass on unto,</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II. The HAPPINESS of a <hi>Virtuous Woman.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And this happiness is here summed up in that Word, <hi>She shall be Praised. Praise,</hi> Reputation, Commendation, is that which a Woman is very tender of; 'tis most appositely then, that the Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:206531:25"/> of a <hi>Virtuous Woman,</hi> are set forth by the <hi>Praise</hi> that should and shall be given her. Said the Apostle of old, <hi>If there be any Virtue, and if there be any Praise, Think on these things.</hi> Truly where there is <hi>Virtue,</hi> there will be <hi>Praise;</hi> and the <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> will have her <hi>Fear</hi> of God, recompensed with <hi>Praise</hi> from God, and be forever <hi>Glorious.</hi> We have these <hi>Conclusions</hi> therefore now before us.</p>
               <div n="1" type="conclusion">
                  <head>Conclusion. 1.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Fear of God</hi> will recommend a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to the <hi>Praise</hi> and so to the <hi>Choice</hi> of such <hi>men,</hi> as it may be <hi>desireable</hi> to have the good Opinion of▪ For a Woman to be <hi>Praised,</hi> is for her to be <hi>Married,</hi> in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Phraseology; thus 'tis Lamented a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Judgments of God, in Ps. 78. 63. <hi>Their Maidens were noc Praised unto Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</hi> Now the <hi>Fear of God</hi> is the best way for a Woman to dispose of her self to such a <hi>Marriage,</hi> as men usually Court none, but such as they hear much <hi>Praised,</hi> unto. When the Scriptuer speaks of the <hi>Marriage</hi> which <hi>Antichrist</hi> forbids unto his Filthy and Wicked <hi>Clergy,</hi> it calls
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:206531:26"/> it. <hi>The desire of Women.</hi> 'Tis that which Women that have any regard unto honour, will <hi>Desire,</hi> with <hi>Disdain</hi> to be otherwise enjoy'd; like that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Woman, who having her Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stity Sollicited, gave that answer, <hi>You must first give me, what you neither have, nor can have your self, and what yet you can give to me;</hi> That was, <hi>A Chast Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</hi> The Truth is, to be <hi>Married</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Vain, Wild, Ungodly man, is that which no Discreet Woman will <hi>Desire;</hi> any more than to dwell with a <hi>Dragon.</hi> The Excellent <hi>Basilla</hi> chose to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, rather than Marry a Pagan Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. But as for Prudent and Pious Men, 'twill be their <hi>Desire</hi> to be Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried unto such a Woman as is eminent for the <hi>Fear of God.</hi> There was a <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> of whom it could be said, in Ruth 3. 11. <hi>All the Town do's know that thou art a Virtuous Woman;</hi> and you know that this Woman was not long with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a good Husband, who had first been taken with her <hi>Praise.</hi> We say, <hi>Matches are made in Heaven;</hi> and indeed the Woman who by the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> has made sure of a great Interest in <hi>Heaven,</hi> is most like to meet with such
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:206531:26"/> a <hi>Match</hi> as may give her cause to thank <hi>Heaven</hi> all her Days. 'Tis possible, that Unsanctify'd men, may Marry on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for <hi>Portion</hi> or for <hi>Prettiness;</hi> how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten do those Respects give us to see <hi>Matches made in Hell!</hi> and yet there are few men so Profane, as to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that <hi>Grace</hi> as undesireable in a <hi>Wife,</hi> of which they themselves are destitute! But men that have the <hi>Fear of God</hi> in themselves, when they chuse the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of their Lives, will ordinarily chuse to have such, as they shall hear <hi>Praised</hi> for, <hi>The Fear of God;</hi> when they do otherwise, the God of <hi>Heaven</hi> often pays 'em severely for it. It is an old Rule,</p>
                  <q>Non solum est Oculis ducenda sed Auribus Ʋxor.</q>
                  <q>(<hi>i. e.</hi>) He that would Marry, and be wise, Must chuse by <hi>Ears,</hi> as well as <hi>Eyes.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>When a man of <hi>Ʋnderstanding,</hi> do's understand that a Woman is <hi>prais'd</hi> for <hi>the fear of God,</hi> this is more than all other <hi>Favour</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> to him; and so she comes to that Room in his well-guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:206531:27"/>
                     <hi>Affection,</hi> which will survive the Death of all other <hi>Favour</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> whatsoever; and which <hi>many Waters can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Quench.</hi> Instead of saying as many do, <hi>There's Money, and we'll hope the fear of God will come in Time;</hi> such a man will say, <hi>There's the fear of God, and we'll hope that all these things will be added:</hi> and if he be an <hi>Isaac,</hi> who <hi>prays</hi> much over and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Marriage, he will pitch upon such a Wife as will not <hi>Hinder</hi> but <hi>Assist</hi> his <hi>Prayers</hi> afterwards. Moreover, the Woman that has, <hi>The fear of God,</hi> need not <hi>Fear,</hi> but that she should be <hi>prais<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d</hi> among multitudes of her other Neighbours whom yet she cannot be <hi>Married</hi> unto. If any do <hi>Deride</hi> her, they are none but those absurd, foolish, giddy Creatures, that will one day change their song, and with bloody Tears will then wish, <hi>O that I had fear'd God like such an one!</hi> All that have any sense of <hi>True-worth,</hi> or, whose <hi>good word</hi> is of any <hi>worth,</hi> will be sure to <hi>Admire</hi> her; 'tis a property in every Citizen of <hi>Zion, He honours them that fear the Lord; but a vile person</hi> [Such an one as do's not <hi>Fear</hi> the Lord▪] <hi>is contemned in his Eyes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="conclusion">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:206531:27"/>
                  <head>Conclusion. 2.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Wisdom</hi> which is in <hi>the fear of God,</hi> makes <hi>Praise</hi> to be the <hi>due</hi> of the Woman that is adorned with it. A <hi>wise</hi> Woman is justly a <hi>Prais'd</hi> Woman, and a <hi>Pris'd</hi> one, all over the World. The <hi>Wise Woman</hi> in the City of <hi>Abel,</hi> doubtless was more than a little Praised in the United Acclamations of that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. 'Tis said in Eccles. 8. 1. <hi>A mans Wisdom makes his Face to shine,</hi> and a <hi>Womans Wisdom</hi> does as much. No <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,</hi> no <hi>Beauty</hi> is comparable to <hi>Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> and tho' a person were all over sparkling with peerless <hi>Pearls,</hi> yet this is a <hi>Favour</hi> and a <hi>Beauty</hi> before which, <hi>No mention shall be made of Pearls; for the price of Wisdom is above Rubies.</hi> Now, who or where is the <hi>Wise Woman?</hi> or what is true <hi>Wisdom?</hi> The <hi>Claim</hi> has been long since laid, by many sorts of witty plodders, and crafty people in the World; but the Apostle has put in that <hi>Bar</hi> unto their claim, <hi>That professing themselves to be Wise, they became Fools.</hi> If the <hi>Politician</hi> may challenge the praise of <hi>Wisdom,</hi> doubtless those four <hi>MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIES</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:206531:28"/> which in the last Age Sway'd the <hi>Scepters</hi> of so many Kingdoms with the Profoundest <hi>Policy,</hi> were <hi>Wise Women,</hi> and the <hi>Elizabeth</hi> which came <hi>after</hi> them, came not <hi>behind</hi> them. <hi>Thomyris</hi> that could lead an Army against the <hi>Persian,</hi> and <hi>Zenobia</hi> that could head an Army against the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour, were <hi>Wise Women.</hi> The <hi>Sabinian</hi> Women which directed the Senate out of inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricable Difficulties, were <hi>Wise</hi> ones. It was a <hi>Wise Woman</hi> of <hi>Tekoa</hi> which could manage an Intreague at Court for the Lord General of <hi>Israel.</hi> If the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher</hi> may Challenge the <hi>Praise</hi> of <hi>Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> doubtless those were <hi>Wise Women</hi> who were <hi>Tutoresses,</hi> if I may call them so, to the old famous Professors of all <hi>Philosophy.</hi> The Daughter of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> who made Comments on her Fathers Books, was a <hi>Wise Woman;</hi> and so was <hi>Hippatia</hi> formerly, who taught the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral Arts, and wrote some Treatises of <hi>Astrology;</hi> and so <hi>Sarocchia</hi> more late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who was ordinarily Moderatrix in the Disputations of the Learned men at <hi>Rome.</hi> The three <hi>Corinnae,</hi> which E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall'd, if not Excell'd the most Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated <hi>Poets</hi> of their Times, were <hi>Wise:</hi>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:206531:28"/> and such Ladies as <hi>Olympias,</hi> or <hi>Trota,</hi> whose Physical skill, was the wonder of the Universe. The Empress <hi>Eudocia,</hi> who Composed Poetical Paraphrases on divers parts of the Bible, was a <hi>Wise Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> so was <hi>Rosuida,</hi> who compiled the <hi>Lives</hi> of Holy men, and <hi>Pamphilia</hi> who Penn'd no Despicable Histories; and the French Lady, who a while since, published Homilies on the Epistle to the <hi>Hebrews;</hi> and thus was the Lady <hi>Jane Grey,</hi> who so admirably could Read the Word of God in its <hi>Originals.</hi> There is <hi>Wisdom</hi> in these things; and the Women which have had it, are therefore to be <hi>Praised.</hi> But, as the Apostle said, <hi>yet I shew unto you a more excellent way;</hi> so I say, <hi>there is a greater Wisdom than all of this.</hi> It is the Asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with which the Wise Man <hi>Begins</hi> the Book of <hi>Wisdom,</hi> in Prov. 1. 7. <hi>The fear of the Lord is the beginning of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> Or as the Words of his blessed Father, whom he much Imitated in his Expressions, were, <hi>The fear of the Lord is the beginning of Wisdom.</hi> Or, as it may be read, <hi>the chief part of it.</hi> Here then, even in, <hi>the fear of God,</hi> is the <hi>Prima Sapientia,</hi> the chief, prime, grand <hi>Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:206531:29"/> of a reasonable Creature. 'Tis a true saying, <hi>Non qui multa, sed qui Fructu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>osa scit, sapit; Wisdom</hi> lies not so much in the Knowledge of <hi>many</hi> things, as in the knowledge of <hi>Ʋseful</hi> ones. Now this is the <hi>Wisdom</hi> of a <hi>Woman</hi> that has <hi>the fear of God;</hi> she has the Science that will carry her safe thro' all the Storms, all the Harms, all the Temptations of this World, unto the Haven of Heaven at the last; she has the <hi>Wisdom,</hi> to <hi>Consider her latter End,</hi> and she is <hi>Wise unto Salvation.</hi> That admirable Woman, <hi>Olympia Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via Morata</hi> had very great accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; but that which most accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plish'd her, was, her embracing of true Religion with all manner of Persecution for it; so that she could say, <hi>the World is now become contemptible to me.</hi> 'Twas <hi>this</hi> alone which Enabled her, when she lay a dying▪ at near thirty years of Age, to see <hi>Heaven</hi> open for her, and say to her Excellent Husband, <hi>I am now full of Joy, and Sir, I know you now no more!</hi> This then is the <hi>Praise</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs unto such a <hi>Woman;</hi> it is noted unto the <hi>praise</hi> of <hi>Abigail, She was a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of a good Ʋnderstanding, and she was of a Beautiful Countenance.</hi> As for the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:206531:29"/> Woman, that has a <hi>Beautiful Countenance</hi> without a <hi>good Understanding,</hi> as for her that is, <hi>Fair and Foolish,</hi> you can find where she is compared unto, <hi>A Swine with a Jewel in her Snout.</hi> But if a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man have <hi>the fear of God,</hi> you now see, that whether she have a <hi>Beautiful Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> or no, yet she has a <hi>good Ʋnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</hi> And therefore such a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man shall be <hi>praised</hi> among those La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies whose <hi>Beautiful</hi> Aspect is particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly mentioned in the Scripture; and whose Names make that <hi>Hexameter</hi> verse,</p>
                  <q>Sarah, Rebecca, Rachel, Abigail, Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shu, Abishag, Esther.</q>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="conclusion">
                  <head>Conclusion. 3.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Benefits</hi> obtained by, <hi>the fear of God,</hi> procure <hi>praises</hi> for the Woman that is endued with it. Said the Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist, in Psal. 31. 19. <hi>O how great is thy goodness, which thou hast laid up for them that fear thee!</hi> Such a <hi>profitable</hi> thing as <hi>the fear of God,</hi> must needs be a <hi>praise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy</hi> thing. Let us a little specifie the <hi>Blessings,</hi> and so the <hi>praises,</hi> which, <hi>the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:206531:30"/> fear of God,</hi> is attended with. As for the Woman that has the <hi>fear of God;</hi> attend now unto the <hi>praises</hi> of such a <hi>Woman.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the Woman whom the Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Lord Jesus Christ becomes, <hi>A Sun of Righteousness</hi> unto. 'Tis said in <hi>Mal. 4. 2. Ʋnto you that Fear my Name, shall the Son of Righteousness arise.</hi> We find among the Representations of the Church, <hi>A Woman clothed with the Sun.</hi> Thus do you now see this <hi>Woman Cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed!</hi> And as by <hi>Union</hi> she is got <hi>into</hi> the Lord Jesus Christ, who like the <hi>Sun</hi> is the <hi>Center</hi> of the World, and who like the <hi>Sun</hi> gives Life and Warmth, and Growth, unto her Soul; so she is by him <hi>Clothed</hi> with all that <hi>Righteousness</hi> which <hi>Delivers from Death.</hi> She not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly has an <hi>Inherent Righteousness,</hi> from the Lord Jesus Christ; or a principle dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing her to render both unto God and Man their <hi>Dues;</hi> but she also has the <hi>Imputed Righteousness</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ, and being by the <hi>Grace</hi> of God allow'd an Interrest in the perfect Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of her Lord, as she now stands as <hi>without Fault before the Throne of God,</hi> Well may she be a <hi>praised Woman,</hi> who
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:206531:30"/> shall be such a <hi>Righteous</hi> one. We say, <hi>The Wife shines with the Husbands Rays.</hi> Behold here a Woman whose <hi>Husband</hi> is, <hi>The Sun of Righteousness.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the Woman whom the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> of Heaven do most gladly <hi>Encamp</hi> about. We have received Information from the <hi>Invisible World,</hi> by Psal. 34. 7. That <hi>the Angel of the Lord Encampeth about them that Fear Him, and delivers them.</hi> A Woman is usually by Law under <hi>Covert;</hi> but it is an <hi>Angelical Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert</hi> which this Woman has by the Law of Heaven placed over her▪ She some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times has an occasion for a <hi>Deliverance;</hi> and the best Angel in Heaven, perhaps the same Angel that visited <hi>Mary</hi> of old, is upon the Wing to hasten it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her. She has a continual, tho' it may be an Insensible Conversation, with <hi>Angels</hi> of better Account, than the <hi>Sons of God,</hi> which were entangled with the <hi>Daughters of Men,</hi> in the <hi>Antediluvian</hi> World; these are her <hi>Guardians,</hi> her <hi>Protectors,</hi> and her Monitors. When she was first Converted unto God, she made <hi>Joy among the Angels,</hi> because of another Spirit come in to fill up the Room left in Heaven by the Apostate
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:206531:31"/> Legions: It gave a Triumph unto those <hi>Morning Stars,</hi> to see one that shall shortly come to move in <hi>Their Orb.</hi> And now she has <hi>Praise among the Angels;</hi> they shout and say, <hi>Here is an Heir of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and we have the welcome and happy care of looking after her.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the Woman, who takes a most <hi>Laudable</hi> course for her own <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral</hi> prosperity. She is to be <hi>Praised</hi> as a <hi>Woman</hi> that prolongs her own <hi>Life.</hi> 'Tis said in Prov. 19. 23. <hi>The Fear of the Lord tendeth to Life.</hi> It keeps her from hastning an Untimely <hi>Death,</hi> upon her self, either by rash Wishes to <hi>Dye,</hi> or by the <hi>overmuch Wickedness</hi> which by the sentence of Providence become <hi>Capital,</hi> or by the <hi>Lusts</hi> which either Drown the <hi>Lamp,</hi> or Burn or Wear the <hi>Thred</hi> of Life away. She is to be <hi>Praised</hi> as a <hi>Woman</hi> that Consults her own <hi>Health.</hi> 'Tis said in <hi>Prov. 3. 7, 8. Fear the Lord—It shall be Health to thy Navel, and Marrow to thy Bones.</hi> It keeps her from the <hi>Sins,</hi> which by being the Parents of <hi>Crudities</hi> and <hi>Obstructions,</hi> are the grand Parents of all Diseases; and being thus <hi>forgiven her Iniquity,</hi> 'tis likely she will not say, <hi>I am sick;</hi> or be forc'd
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:206531:31"/> like the Woman in the Gospel, <hi>To spend all upon Physicians.</hi> She is to be <hi>Praised</hi> as a <hi>Woman</hi> that Preserves her own <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</hi> 'Tis said in Prov. 22. 4. <hi>By the Fear of the Lord is Honour.</hi> It makes her acknowledged for one that has the <hi>Image</hi> of Christ and God upon her; which is <hi>The One Thing</hi> that renders <hi>Honourable;</hi> and while she makes it her business like another <hi>Dorcas</hi> to <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> her Master, He fulfills that word unto her, <hi>Them that honour me, I will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour;</hi> and leaves her not cause for that complaint, <hi>Reproach has broken my Heart.</hi> She is to be <hi>praised</hi> as a <hi>Woman</hi> that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually lays in for her self a Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and Convenient Portion of <hi>Worldly Comforts.</hi> 'Tis said in Psal. 101. 5. <hi>The Lord hath given Meat unto them that Fear him.</hi> She will not be one of the <hi>Idle Souls that suffer Hunger;</hi> but according to Gods <hi>Promise,</hi> which is her <hi>Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house,</hi> her House has in it, all the sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies which are needful for her Glorify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God; and having as much <hi>Manna</hi> as will carry her through the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, she do's not Crave after those <hi>Cumbersome Additions,</hi> which may hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her passing <hi>through the Eye of the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:206531:32"/> Needle:</hi> the <hi>Young Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ns</hi> have not so good a <hi>Table!</hi> she is to be <hi>praised</hi> as a <hi>Woman</hi> that procures a <hi>special Guard</hi> of God upon her, in an <hi>Evil Day.</hi> 'Tis said in Psal. 33. 18, 19. <hi>The Eye of the Lord is upon them that Fear him,—to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver their Soul from Death, and to keep them alive in Famine.</hi> Let things go ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so bad, she can with <hi>Isaiah</hi> sing, <hi>the Forty Sixth Psalm,</hi> as being one of the <hi>Alamoth,</hi> or <hi>Head Persons,</hi> concerned in it; she has the Blood of our <hi>Passover</hi> apply'd unto her, and so she is <hi>preserv'd in Christ Jesus,</hi> when the Destroying Angels are the Executioners of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wrath abroad; She has <hi>Rahab</hi>'s Threed for her Defence in the midst of Wasting Plagues, and she has a <hi>Mark upon her Forehead</hi> [which I am sure the Garish Attire <hi>there</hi> used in our Days is not!] for her <hi>Preservation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the Woman, who takes a most <hi>Laudable</hi> way for her own <hi>Eternal</hi> Prosperity too. She is to be <hi>praised,</hi> as a <hi>Woman</hi> that has made her <hi>Peace</hi> with God. It is said in Psal. 103. 11, 12. <hi>Great is his Mercy towards them that fear him, As far as the East is from the West, so far hath he removed our Transgressions
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:206531:32"/> from us.</hi> He that was <hi>Born of a Woman</hi> has made satisfaction for all the Wrongs that her Sins have done to the most Holy Lord; God for the sake of Christ has <hi>Releas'd</hi> her from whatever <hi>Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> was ever due unto her, for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>Transgression</hi> of his Law; and thus, <hi>Being Justified by Faith, she has Peace with God.</hi> If any Afflictions come upon her, there are not <hi>Vindictive</hi> or <hi>Destructive,</hi> but purely <hi>Medicinal;</hi> She sees they are <hi>to do her good in the latter end;</hi> they are <hi>to make her partaker of Gods holiness;</hi> they are <hi>to Work for her a far more Exceeding and Eternal Weight of Glory.</hi> She says like the Martyr, <hi>God is now Scowring of me, to set me bright on an high Shelf in Heaven for ever.</hi> She is to be <hi>prais'd</hi> as a <hi>Woman</hi> that is heard in her <hi>Prayer</hi> to God. It is said in Psal. 145. 19. <hi>He will fulfil the Desire of them that fear him, he also will hear their Cry, and he will save them.</hi> She is one who has her Hearts <hi>Delight</hi> in God, and so she has her Hearts <hi>Desire</hi> from God. Her <hi>Prayers</hi> are the <hi>Breathings</hi> which the Spirit of God have Enkindled in her, and the Power, and Wisdom of God, either in the <hi>Letter,</hi> or in the <hi>Better</hi> gives a good answer to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:206531:33"/> them all; the Almighty gives her a <hi>Right Will,</hi> which inclines her to ask of him, <hi>thing according to his Will;</hi> and then he says, as unto <hi>Her</hi> of old, <hi>Be it unto thee, even as thou wilt.</hi> She is to be <hi>praised,</hi> as a <hi>Woman</hi> that gets her Soul Replenished with such <hi>Comforts</hi> as have a Fore taste of Heaven in them. It is said in Act. 9. 31. <hi>They were Edify'd, walking in the fear of God, and in the comfort of the Holy Ghost.</hi> The Holy Ghost <hi>Seals</hi> her with well-grounded and effectual persuasions of Gods hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Loved her with an Everlasting Love.</hi> Hence, whatever troubles do come upon her, she feels a <hi>Word</hi> set home upon her, which causes her like <hi>Hannah,</hi> to be <hi>no more sad.</hi> She is to be <hi>Praised,</hi> as a <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> whom the <hi>Day of Judgment</hi> will bring Wonderful <hi>Glories</hi> and <hi>Rewards</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. It is said in Rev. 11. 18. <hi>The time of the Dead, that they should be Judged is come, that thou shouldest give reward unto them that Fear thy Name, small and great.</hi> She shall be one of the <hi>Early Risers</hi> in that <hi>Morning</hi> of the great Day; when the <hi>Change</hi> for which her departed Soul has been waiting, is <hi>come,</hi> her Lord-Redeemer, shall say to her, <hi>Awake and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:206531:33"/> Sing▪ thou that dwellest in the Dust;</hi> and she shall then be marvellously <hi>Changed into the Likeness of the Lord Jesus Christ Himself;</hi> She shall be made what <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> appeared in the Mount of God; The Lord Jesus will then openly Absolve her and Applaud her; and she shall sit with him on a <hi>Throne in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation;</hi> her Heart may <hi>now</hi> even spring like <hi>John</hi> in his Mothers Belly, when she foresees the Approaches of the Lord. She is to be <hi>Praised,</hi> as a <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> who is to be made partaker of <hi>Life Eternal.</hi> It is said in <hi>Prov. 14. 27. The Fear of the Lord, is a Fountain of Life, to depart from the Snares of Death. Her Spirit</hi> shall be entertained with a trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming and refreshing <hi>Vision</hi> of God in the Lord Jesus Christ, amidst the Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestial Regions of <hi>Light,</hi> with all the Sacred <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of those Regions. Her <hi>Body,</hi> shall also be made <hi>Incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible,</hi> and more Immortal than ever <hi>Eves</hi> in <hi>Eden</hi> was; it shall be made <hi>Powerful, Fulgent, Nimble, Subtile, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual,</hi> and after a sort <hi>Angelical.</hi> So shall she have a <hi>Fulness of Joy in the Presence of God, and Pleasures at his Right Hand for ever more.</hi> Here is the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:206531:34"/> that has the <hi>Fear of God!</hi> This is the <hi>Praise</hi> that belongs unto her.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>APPLICATION.</head>
               <p>But shall it now be seen, that <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> will more generally aspire after this <hi>Character</hi> and this <hi>Happiness?</hi> The petu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Pens of some Froward and Morose Men, have sometimes treated the <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Sex</hi> with very great Indignities; <hi>Blades,</hi> I guess, whose <hi>Mothers</hi> had Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutiful <hi>Children,</hi> or whose <hi>Wives</hi> have had but cruel <hi>Masters.</hi> I am loth to shew my <hi>Catalogue,</hi> nevertheless whole <hi>Volumns</hi> have been written, to disgrace that <hi>Sex,</hi> as if it were, as one of those <hi>Ʋnnatural Authors</hi> calls it, <hi>The meer Confusion of Mankind.</hi> Yea, 'tis not easie to recount how many Licentious Writers, have handled that <hi>Theme, Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina nulla bona, No Woman is good!</hi> [or the men were bad that said so] But, behold, how you may recover your Impaired Reputation! the <hi>Fear of God</hi> will soon make it evident, that you are among <hi>the Excellent in the Earth.</hi> If any men are so wicked (and some Sects of men have so) as to deny your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:206531:34"/>
                  <hi>Rational</hi> Creatures, the best means to consure them, will be by proving your selves <hi>Religious</hi> ones. I do assure you, and I have more than <hi>Luther</hi> to consent and concur with me, in this assertion, <hi>That the Actions of even the meanest Milk-maid or Cook-maid, when done in the</hi> Fear of God, <hi>are in the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of God more Noble Things than the Victories of a Caesar!</hi> Thus do I set be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, the way for you to be <hi>En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled;</hi> and thus <hi>Ennobled,</hi> many of you already are. When the <hi>Golden-mouth'd</hi> Ancient had so far forgot himself as to call a Woman, <hi>An Ʋnavoidable Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a Necessary Evil, a Desireable Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity:</hi> With more such <hi>Iron words,</hi> he sees cause to add, <hi>Sermo est de muliere mala;—My Speech is of a bad Woman; and not of a good; for I have known many ready to every good Work.</hi> 'Tis an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of <hi>Solomons</hi> which has been somewhat Improv'd against you, in <hi>Eccles. 7. 28. One man among a Thousand have I found, but a Woman among all those have I not found.</hi> Nevertheless, in your own Vindication, you may reply, that <hi>Solomon</hi> speaks of what is usual about the <hi>Courts</hi> of Princes; and perhaps
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:206531:35"/> about his own <hi>Court</hi> especially; A <hi>good</hi> man in such a place is a <hi>rare</hi> thing; but a <hi>good Woman</hi> there, is a <hi>black Swan</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; <hi>Solomon</hi> himself Particularly had a <hi>Thousand Women</hi> to satiate his Exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Lust; and possibly he may intimate, that among all <hi>those</hi> he did not find <hi>One Woman</hi> truly <hi>Vertuous.</hi> Or, if this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply be not satisfactory, you may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, whether <hi>Solomon</hi> spake not of such as are by Repentance recovered from the <hi>Snares</hi> of <hi>Whoredom,</hi> when once they have been therein entangled. For a <hi>Man</hi> to be reclaimed from the Sin of <hi>Ʋncleanness</hi> when once he has been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thereunto is <hi>rare;</hi> but for a <hi>Woman</hi> to be snatch'd out of the <hi>Ʋnclean</hi> Devils Hands, when once he has had any full <hi>Possession</hi> of her, is more extraordinary! However it be, 'tis plain, that as there were three <hi>Maries</hi> to one <hi>John,</hi> stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ng under the Cross of our Dying Lord, so still there are far more <hi>godly Women</hi> in the World, than there are <hi>godly Men;</hi> and our <hi>Church Communions</hi> give us a little demonstration of it. I have seen it without going a Mile from home, that in a Church of between <hi>Three</hi> or <hi>Four</hi> Hundred <hi>Communicants,</hi> there are
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:206531:35"/> but few more than <hi>One</hi> Hundred <hi>Men;</hi> all the rest are <hi>Women,</hi> of whom <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rity</hi> will <hi>think no Evil.</hi> Possibly, <hi>One</hi> reason of it is, because there are <hi>more</hi> Women in the World than Men; but this is not <hi>all</hi> the reason. It seems that the <hi>Curse</hi> in the Difficulties both of <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi> and of <hi>Child-bearing,</hi> which the <hi>Female Sex</hi> is doom'd unto, has been turn'd into a <hi>Blessing,</hi> by the <hi>Free Grace</hi> of our most Gracious God. God sanctifies the <hi>Chains,</hi> the <hi>Pains,</hi> the <hi>Deaths</hi> which they meet withal; and furthermore, makes the <hi>Tenderness</hi> of their Disposition, a further occasion of serious Devotion in them. Now, God forbid that any of YOU, into whose Hands this little Treatise may come, should Contradict that <hi>Charitable Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> And let me tell you, that most of You, have more <hi>Time</hi> to employ in the more Immediate Service of your Souls, than the <hi>other Sex</hi> is owner of, You are Ordinarily more within the <hi>House,</hi> and so may more mind the Work within the <hi>Heart,</hi> than <hi>We.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I must Confess, 'tis <hi>often</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise; Yet it is as <hi>often</hi> so, that you have little more Worldly Business, than to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:206531:36"/>
                  <hi>Spend</hi> [I should rather say, to <hi>Save</hi>] what others <hi>Get,</hi> and to <hi>Dress</hi> and <hi>Feed</hi> [should I not also say, to <hi>Teach</hi>] the little Birds, which you are <hi>Dams</hi> unto. And those of you that are <hi>Women of Quality</hi> are excused from very much of <hi>this</hi> Trouble too. Oh! how much might you do for <hi>GOD</hi> if you duely considered, <hi>The Price in your Hands to get Wisdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well then,</p>
               <div n="1" type="counsel">
                  <head>Counsel. 1.</head>
                  <p>The First thing unto which I would persuade you, is, to <hi>Pray</hi> most Instantly, Constantly, Importunately that <hi>the Fear of God,</hi> may be Planted in your Souls. The <hi>Fear of God,</hi> is indeed already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in that Soul, which is insatiably <hi>desirous</hi> to be therewith replenished; and <hi>Ʋnutterable Groans</hi> after that <hi>Fear,</hi> will augment the <hi>Power</hi> of that, which it already argues the <hi>Presence</hi> of. Said <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> in <hi>Chap. 1. 11. O Lord, be Attentive to the Prayer of thy Servants, who desire to Fear thy Name.</hi> The Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that most affectionately lays this
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:206531:36"/>
                     <hi>desire</hi> before God, <hi>O that I may Fear thy Name,</hi> is already among the <hi>Servants</hi> of that God, and shall certainly have her <hi>desire accomplish'd.</hi> Pray Read, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, Practise that Word of God, in <hi>Prov. 2. 3, 5. If thou Cryest after Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, then shalt thou understand the Fear of the Lord. Crying</hi> is that which your Sex has its particular <hi>Easiness</hi> unto; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, what your <hi>Cries,</hi> your <hi>Tears</hi> are best employ'd about. May it then be said about you, <hi>Behold she prays.</hi> and may your <hi>Prayer</hi> to the Lord put in suit that <hi>Promise</hi> of the Lord, in <hi>Jer. 32. 40. I will put my Fear in their Hearts.</hi> O plead earnestly for the fulfilment of that <hi>Great and Precious</hi> Word of our God, and say, <hi>Lord, Be it unto thy Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid according to thy Word.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="counsel">
                  <head>Counsel. 2.</head>
                  <p>Having obtain'd the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> it should be your Ambition to be <hi>continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally exercising</hi> of it. You are thus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised in <hi>Prov. 23. 17. Be thou in the Fear of the Lord all the day long.</hi> Let your whole walk every Day, be a <hi>Walk with God;</hi> and let every action in the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:206531:37"/> day, be so done in the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> as that <hi>Holiness to the Lord,</hi> may be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thereupon. Be sure to <hi>Begin</hi> and <hi>Conclude</hi> the Day with God; Rob him not of his <hi>Daily Sacrifice.</hi> In the <hi>Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> be able to say, <hi>Oh God, when I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake I am still with thee;</hi> take a <hi>Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings Dranght</hi> of Communion with God, first in your <hi>Closets,</hi> and then with your <hi>Houses,</hi> and of resolution to behave your selves as having <hi>The Lord always before you.</hi> In the <hi>Evening,</hi> recollect the <hi>Mercies</hi> which you have newly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of God; and <hi>Examine</hi> whether you have been so <hi>Zealous, Watchful, Fruitful</hi> before God, as you should have been? and whether you can <hi>lye down in Peace with Him?</hi> Throughout all the Day, Interweave a <hi>Conscience of Duty,</hi> into all your motions, all your affairs. Let every <hi>Meal,</hi> every <hi>Sleep,</hi> every <hi>Visit,</hi> and all your <hi>Domestick Businesses,</hi> though it be but the Rocking of a <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle,</hi> be done with an Eye to this, <hi>This is the Thing wherein I may perform a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to God, and expect a Blessing from God; This is what my God would have me to be about.</hi> Herewithal, intermingle many <hi>Salleys</hi> of Soul, towards Heaven
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:206531:37"/> every day; by raising of some serious gracious, divine <hi>Thoughts</hi> from the meanest occurrents that are before you; and by Pertinent <hi>Ejaculations</hi> to God, both in a way of <hi>Petition</hi> and of <hi>Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving</hi> upon all Occasions. This 'tis to be, <hi>In the Fear of the Lord all the Day long,</hi> and <hi>Holy in every Turn!</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="counsel">
                  <head>Counsel. 3.</head>
                  <p>But at the same time you should use a good <hi>Caution</hi> against those that would <hi>Seduce</hi> you from the <hi>Fear of God.</hi> It is mention'd as the singular unhappiness of Women, in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 6. Men <hi>having a Form of Godliness, but denying the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er thereof,</hi>—These <hi>Creep</hi> [like Serpents, as they are] <hi>into Houses, and lead Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Silly Women, laden with Sins, led away with diverse Lusts.</hi> 'Tis noted of <hi>Seducers,</hi> that like their Father the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, the Old, the First <hi>Seducer,</hi> they have a special design upon the <hi>Weaker Sex,</hi> who are most easily <hi>gained</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and then fit Instruments for the <hi>gaining</hi> of their Husbands, to such Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors as cause them to <hi>lose</hi> their Souls at last. <hi>Simon Magus</hi> Traded with his <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena,</hi>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:206531:38"/> and <hi>Montanus</hi> with his <hi>Maximilla,</hi> for the more effectual Propagation of their Heresies, as <hi>Jerom</hi> long since ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served; and as <hi>Ephiphanius</hi> tells us, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> promoted his Blasphemies by first Proselyting seven hundred Virgins there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. That it is no new thing for <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> to become very mischievous Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries unto the <hi>Truth,</hi> and so unto the <hi>Fear</hi> of God, is intimated from that instance in the Apostolical History, <hi>Acts 13. 51. The Jews stirred up the Devout and Honour able Women, and raised a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution against</hi> the Ministers of God. Indeed a <hi>Poison</hi> does never insinuate so quickly, or operate so strongly, as when <hi>Womans Milk</hi> is the Vehicle, which 'tis given in. But may <hi>You</hi> be always upon your <hi>Guard,</hi> against the <hi>False Teachers</hi> in these Days; and therefore become so well principled in your <hi>Catechisms,</hi> as that it may not be said of you, <hi>They are ever Learning and never able to come unto the Knowledge of the Truth.</hi> If you find your selves unable to fathom some <hi>Controversies</hi> which you see agitated in the Church of God, and if you must cry out, <hi>I have nothing to draw with, and the Well is deep,</hi> the most likely way to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:206531:38"/> be kept from going out of the Way, is <hi>This;</hi> mind what has the most obvious tendency to advance the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> in your Hearts and Lives; mind what most magnifies <hi>Christ</hi> and nullifies <hi>Man,</hi> and recommends <hi>Practical Godliness;</hi> 'tis the <hi>Doctrine according to Godliness,</hi> which is the <hi>True Doctrine.</hi> Or if thou can't Penetrate so far, then mind how those men which are most eminent for the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> are most generally inclin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; mind what is most generally grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the <hi>Sober,</hi> Gracious, Patient, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, Mortify'd part of Mankind; and on the other side, what the most <hi>Loose,</hi> Proud, Carnal, Railing, Profane, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty chuse to fall in withal; to <hi>Walk in the Way of good Men:</hi> is most probably to <hi>Walk in the good Way.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="counsel">
                  <head>Counsel. 4.</head>
                  <p>While you thus maintain the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> let it very particularly discover it self in your keeping the purpose of the Psalmist, <hi>I will take heed unto my ways that I Sin not with my Tongue; I will keep my Mouth with a Bridle.</hi> May it be as much a <hi>Causeless,</hi> as it is a <hi>Common</hi> report
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:206531:39"/> concerning you, that your <hi>Tongues</hi> are frequently not so governed by the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> as they ought to be. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of <hi>Speech</hi> is of such a Noble and of such a signal Figure in the constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Mankind,</hi> that it is a thousand pitys, it should be <hi>Abus'd;</hi> but <hi>Woman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind</hi> is usually charged with a peculiar share in the Worlds <hi>Abuses</hi> of it. It is indeed a piece of great Injustice, that every Woman should be so far an <hi>Eve,</hi> as that <hi>her</hi> Depravation should be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto <hi>all</hi> the Sex. Nevertheless it highly concerns you to do your part, that in <hi>Fames</hi> Trumpet, which is a <hi>Speaking</hi> One, you may be better <hi>spoken</hi> of, as to the matter of your <hi>speaking.</hi> The attainment which therefore I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend unto you, is that in <hi>Prov. 10. 20. The Tongue of the Just, is as choice Silver.</hi> A <hi>Woman</hi> is often valued according to the <hi>Silver</hi> that she has to bring unto them that will call her their <hi>Mistress,</hi> in order to their being <hi>Master</hi> of that. 'Tis a few <hi>Pounds, Shilling and Pence,</hi> that makes her weigh heaviest in the Scale of the vulgar Estimation. But a <hi>Woman</hi> of a <hi>Silver Tongue</hi> is the person of whom we may most reasonably say, <hi>She is
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:206531:39"/> not of little worth.</hi> As your <hi>Speech</hi> ought always to be <hi>True,</hi> and there should be no less an agreement between your <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Words,</hi> than between your <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Things,</hi> ever speaking <hi>As</hi> you think, tho' it may be not <hi>All</hi> you think; lest you put <hi>Brass</hi> or <hi>Tin</hi> instead of <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver:</hi> so your <hi>Speech</hi> ought likewise to be <hi>Rare,</hi> like <hi>Silver,</hi> which is not so common as <hi>Copper</hi> or <hi>Iron</hi> is. Be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that you don't <hi>Speak too soon,</hi> because you cannot fetch back and eat up, what is uttered; but <hi>Study to Answer.</hi> And be careful that you don't <hi>Speak too much,</hi> because that when the Chest is always <hi>open,</hi> every one counts there are no Treasures in it; and the Scripture tells us, 'tis the <hi>Whore</hi> that is <hi>Clamorous,</hi> and the <hi>Fool,</hi> that is <hi>full of words.</hi> Let there be a comely <hi>Affability</hi> and <hi>Ingenuity</hi> at the same time, in all your <hi>Spe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ch,</hi> that it may be as <hi>grateful</hi> as a Bag of <hi>Silver</hi> would be to the Receivers of it; and O let there be no <hi>Dross</hi> in your whole <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication.</hi> The <hi>Dross</hi> of your own <hi>Wrath,</hi> vented in scolding, fury, vile names; the <hi>Dross</hi> of your own <hi>Worth,</hi> vented in boasting, bragging, self-osten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; the <hi>Dross</hi> of all <hi>Filthiness,</hi> vent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:206531:40"/> in Baudy Talk about the Things which 'tis a <hi>shame to speak;</hi> let all this <hi>Dross</hi> be purged out of all your <hi>Speech.</hi> But instead thereof let your <hi>Speech,</hi> have so much <hi>Ʋse</hi> in it, that your Discourse may bring as much Emolument as ready <hi>Silver</hi> to the Hearers of it; that your <hi>Lips</hi> may <hi>Feed many,</hi> your <hi>Mouth</hi> may be a <hi>Well of Life,</hi> and your <hi>Tongue</hi> may be <hi>Health:</hi> and that ordinarily your Companions may not be a Quarter of an hour with you, before they may have cause to say of you, <hi>Her Discourse has been Meat, Drink and Physick to my Soul!</hi> O that when you are talking you would imagine what the Prophet says, <hi>The Lord hearkened and heard,</hi> and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge what the Psalmist owns, <hi>There is not a Word in my Tongue, but behold O Lord, thou knowest it altogether.</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Tertullian</hi> relates, That the Primitive Christians did use to <hi>season</hi> their <hi>Feasts with</hi> very savoury Discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses; and he gives this reason for it; <hi>Ita fabulantur, ut qui sciant Dominum audire;</hi> They <hi>Talk</hi> as knowing that the Lord <hi>Hears.</hi> Pray carry <hi>that</hi> in your Minds, and <hi>that</hi> will prevent the Impertinent <hi>Gossiping</hi> which you have been reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:206531:40"/> for, <hi>that</hi> will make you bring forth such things as you may with Joy find entred in <hi>The Lords Books of Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="counsel">
                  <head>Counsel 5.</head>
                  <p>There is one particular thing more, which you shall see that your <hi>fear of God,</hi> extends it self unto; and that is, your APPAREL, which you are often accused for <hi>transgressing</hi> in. Where the <hi>fear of God</hi> sanctifies the <hi>Heart,</hi> it will doubtless regulate the <hi>Habit.</hi> Pray let the <hi>fear of</hi> God, make you able to stand before the <hi>VVord of God;</hi> where <hi>VVo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> are commanded in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 2, 3, 4. to have <hi>a chast Conversation coupled with fear;</hi> whose <hi>Adorning</hi> ('tis added) <hi>let it not be the outward Adorning, but let it be the hidden man of the heart. For after this manner in the old Time, the holy women also who trusted in God, adorned themselves.</hi> And in 1 <hi>Tim. 2. 9. That they adorn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in modest Apparel with shame-faced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and sobriety; not with broidered Hair, or Gold, or Pearls, or costly Array; but (which becometh women professing godliness) with good works.</hi> 'Tis true, that more
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:206531:41"/>
                     <hi>Indulgence</hi> may be given to <hi>VVomen</hi> and <hi>Children</hi> in point of <hi>Apparel,</hi> than to <hi>Men;</hi> they were the <hi>VVives,</hi> and the <hi>little Sons</hi> and the <hi>Daughters,</hi> which we find wearing most of <hi>Ornament</hi> among the Antient People of God; and yet unto <hi>you</hi> also, has the God of Heaven given a <hi>Law,</hi> agreeably to which you are to Attire your selves. You shall permit me to lay before you, a few <hi>Maxims,</hi> every One of which are so many just <hi>Consequences</hi> from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that have been given you.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. For a Woman to expose unto <hi>Com-View</hi> those parts of her Body, which there can be no good <hi>End</hi> or <hi>Ʋse</hi> for the Exposing of, is for her to expose her self unto the Vengeance of Heaven. There is indeed a <hi>covering</hi> of the <hi>Skin,</hi> which is but a <hi>black Mark</hi> of one that never yet had a <hi>covering</hi> for her <hi>Sin.</hi> The <hi>black Patches</hi> worn by too many Females, are indeed so many <hi>blew</hi> ones; they are the <hi>Tokens</hi> of a Plague in the Soul. They are not, <hi>the spots</hi> of <hi>Gods Children,</hi> but the Dapples of a <hi>Leopard</hi> that will never, <hi>learn to do well.</hi> They are for the most part upon the <hi>Faces</hi> that never were washed in the Blood of the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:206531:41"/>
                     <hi>Lamb without Spot;</hi> nor do they argue the Soul within to be one unto whom our Lord may say, <hi>Thou art all fair there is no spot in thee.</hi> But there is a <hi>Nakedness</hi> of the <hi>Skin</hi> which is also, and as much to be accounted Criminal. The <hi>Face</hi> is to be Naked because of what is to be <hi>known</hi> by it; the <hi>Hands</hi> are to be Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, because of what is to be <hi>done</hi> by them. But for the Nakedness of the <hi>Back</hi> and <hi>Breasts,</hi> no reason can be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; unless it be that a Woman may by showing a <hi>Fair-skin</hi> enkindle a <hi>Foul Fire</hi> in the Male Spectators; for which cause even <hi>Popish Writers</hi> have no less Righteously than severely <hi>Lashed</hi> them; and for <hi>Protestant Women</hi> to <hi>use</hi> them, is no less inexcusable than it is abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: nor did a <hi>Golden Mouth</hi> of old stick to say, <hi>The Devil sat upon them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. For a Woman to put her self into a <hi>Fashion,</hi> that shall prejudice, either her <hi>Health,</hi> or her <hi>Work.</hi> is to break all the other Eight Commandments as well as the <hi>Sixth</hi> and the <hi>Eighth,</hi> which are thereby notoriously violated. They that say, <hi>Pride feels no Cold,</hi> do often catch a <hi>Mortal Cold</hi> that they may please a foolish <hi>Pride,</hi> and the <hi>Heat</hi> of Hell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flames
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:206531:42"/> is that which they thus hasten up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themselves. They that profanely say, <hi>As good out of the World as out of the Fashion,</hi> often follow such a <hi>Fashion</hi> as either <hi>hurries</hi> them out of the World, or <hi>unfits</hi> them for living in it. Creatures yet, than which none would be more loth to put on such a <hi>Pitch'd Coat of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome,</hi> as <hi>Nero</hi> clapp'd on the Backs of them that Worshipped our blessed Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus to burn them in it. But what account can they give at last? when Women go so, that they cannot <hi>Eat</hi> or <hi>Breath,</hi> be sure they cannot <hi>Work;</hi> and it is just with God that they who cannot thus <hi>Work,</hi> should not be permitted long to <hi>Eat</hi> or <hi>Breath.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. For a Woman to Wear what is not evidently, consistent with <hi>Modesty, Gravity,</hi> and <hi>Sobriety,</hi> is to wear not an <hi>Ornament,</hi> but a <hi>Defilement;</hi> and she puts off those Glorious <hi>Virtues,</hi> when she puts on the Visible <hi>Badges</hi> of what is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thereunto. The command which requires any <hi>Grace,</hi> requires also the Sign of that <hi>Grace;</hi> hence for a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with her Garish, Pompous, Flant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Modes, to <hi>hang out the Sign,</hi> upon which every Rational Beholder thinks
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:206531:42"/> he has Liberty to Read, <hi>There dwells a Proud, Light, Vain, Giddy, Trifling Soul, in that Carcase!</hi> this is not according to God; who says, <hi>Whatsoever things are Venerable, whatsoever things are Lovely, whatsoever things are of Good Report, think of these things.</hi> They that would approve themselves. <hi>The Daughters of Abraham,</hi> are to be <hi>The Daughters of Sarah</hi> too.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. As a <hi>Poor</hi> Woman may not as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire to go with a Bravery, which a <hi>rich</hi> or a <hi>great</hi> Woman may be allowed in, so neither may a <hi>rich</hi> or a <hi>great</hi> Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man extend her Bravery, beyond the allowance which God has given her. There is a <hi>Soft-Cloathing</hi> which our Lord Jesus does not seem to deny unto such Persons of Quality as are in <hi>Kings-Houses.</hi> But you have doubtless heard, what came of the <hi>Frog,</hi> which would not be content, except she might look as big as the <hi>Cow.</hi> The <hi>Ranks</hi> of People should be discerned by their <hi>Cloaths;</hi> nor should we go in any things but what may be called <hi>Suits.</hi> The Woman which will go as none but those who are <hi>above</hi> her, do or can, shews her self to be as much out of her <hi>Wits</hi> as out of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:206531:43"/> her <hi>Place.</hi> And she that will not <hi>Cut her Coat according to her Cloath,</hi> does but put a <hi>Fools Coat</hi> upon her; she that will have more on her <hi>Back,</hi> than can rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily come out of her <hi>Purse,</hi> deserves to be stript as the Fine <hi>Jay</hi> was of her bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row'd Feathers. Nevertheless, <hi>Vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory</hi> may insinuate it self into the <hi>rich</hi> and <hi>great,</hi> as well as the <hi>poor;</hi> and I am to <hi>Charge</hi> THEM, <hi>That they be not High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">V. A Woman, whose Raiment is too <hi>Costly</hi> to leave her capable of attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Duties of <hi>Justice</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> commits but a piece of shining <hi>Thievery,</hi> in that cheating and cruel <hi>Finery.</hi> She that through Excesses in <hi>Attiring</hi> of her self, is unfitted for the payment of what she <hi>owes,</hi> either to her private <hi>Creditors,</hi> or to the support of the <hi>Government</hi> and the <hi>Ministry,</hi> by which her <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Sacred</hi> well-fare is watch'd unto, is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly unworthy, either of <hi>Credit,</hi> or of any <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Sacred</hi> advantages. But there are <hi>Works of Charity</hi> as well as <hi>Works of Righteousness,</hi> which a Woman is also under such obligation to, that all <hi>Supe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities</hi> are to be retrenched for the sake thereof. It seems but reasonable that
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:206531:43"/> whenever we lay out any thing for <hi>purely Ornamental Superfluities,</hi> we should lay out as much in <hi>Cloathing</hi> and <hi>Feeding</hi> the distressed Members of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ; I doubt we shall make up very mean Accounts about our <hi>Talents,</hi> if we do not so.</p>
                  <p n="6">VI. For an <hi>old</hi> Woman to flaunt it in a <hi>Youthful</hi> dress, is altogether as prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious a Disorder, as for the <hi>Flowers</hi> of <hi>May</hi> to appear among the <hi>Snows</hi> of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember.</hi> A <hi>Summer Dress</hi> will not <hi>suit</hi> a <hi>Winter Age.</hi> The Aged shew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to be <hi>twice Children,</hi> indeed, if they go like <hi>Children,</hi> and not <hi>put away Childish things.</hi> For a VVoman that knows her self near her <hi>Winding Sheet,</hi> still to affect a <hi>Wedding Robe,</hi> is a Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness than which there can be nothing more uncomely.</p>
                  <p n="7">VII. For a <hi>Pious</hi> VVoman to <hi>Preserve</hi> no <hi>Distinction</hi> from a <hi>Debaucht</hi> one, in her Apparel, where it may be done, is to leave her self without a <hi>Dislinction</hi> which might <hi>preserve</hi> her when the common and wasting Judgments of God are <hi>Punishing the strange Apparel</hi> in her Neighbourhood. It was well advised by <hi>Tertullian</hi> to the Matrons in his Days,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:206531:44"/>
                     <hi>Ut sit inter Ancillas Dei &amp; Diaboli Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimen,</hi> that the <hi>Handmaids</hi> of <hi>God</hi> would go so as to distinguish themselves from the <hi>Handmaids</hi> of the <hi>Devil;</hi> and believe it, the plagues which come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Haughty Daughters of Zion,</hi> will make no difference between those that make none for themselves. VVe read concerning <hi>the Attire of the Harlot;</hi> and the VVoman that will <hi>Wear</hi> like such an one, will probably <hi>Fare</hi> like her in her Calamities. The <hi>Courtesans</hi> in some Nations of old, were known by <hi>Vails</hi> of a particular shape; and it is pity but that <hi>Vertuous</hi> People should agree to avoid such Habits, as <hi>Vicious</hi> persons have signalized themselves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
                  <p n="8">VIII. VVhen a VVoman finds her Superfluous <hi>Accoutrements,</hi> to excite any <hi>Lust</hi> in her self, she should no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger carry about her the Flint and Steel that strike Fire into the <hi>Tinder</hi> of her Corruptions. If <hi>Maries</hi> Locks have entangled her self or others, it becomes her to turn them into a <hi>Towel</hi> for the feet of the Lord Jesus. To nourish and foment any Distemper in our minds, is for us to <hi>Wrong our own Souls,</hi> with a
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:206531:44"/> Phrensy greater than that of the Posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Creature, which kept <hi>Cuting and Wounding</hi> himself among the Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Dead. For a VVoman to indulge her self in a <hi>Gaiety,</hi> which as often as 'tis put on, disposes her Soul to such a <hi>Vanity,</hi> as indisposes her to Devotion, or throws her into a frame disagreeable to that of a <hi>Stranger</hi> and a <hi>Pilgrim</hi> in the VVorld; this truly does not <hi>Adorn the Doctrine of God our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">IX. The VVoman that must be the <hi>Highest</hi> or the <hi>soonest</hi> in every <hi>New Fashion,</hi> will herein always keep the <hi>Old Fashion</hi> of a <hi>Proud Fool.</hi> It is required of us, <hi>Let your Moderation be known unto all men,</hi> but for a VVoman to betray such a <hi>Levity,</hi> that nothing will please her but <hi>Changeable Taffata;</hi> and it shall be as easie to <hi>make a Coat for the Moon</hi> as to accommodate her fickle Humour with <hi>One</hi> unto her mind; or for her to betray such an <hi>Ambition,</hi> that none shall come to <hi>her</hi> Dimensions without an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servable Exorbitancy.—this is quite contrary to a <hi>Chrisiian Moderation.</hi> If when our Lord should say, <hi>She seeks me early,</hi> 'tis only the Gallantry of the Age
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:206531:45"/> that can say, <hi>She is an early seeker of me;</hi> if when our Lord asketh of her, <hi>What dost thou more than others?</hi> all her An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer must be, <hi>I flaunt it more, and I brave it more!</hi> 'tis but a miserable story that is to be told of her.</p>
                  <p n="10">X. If a VVoman spend more time in <hi>Dressing,</hi> than she does in <hi>Praying,</hi> or in <hi>Working out her own Salvation,</hi> her <hi>Dress</hi> is but the Snare of her <hi>Soul.</hi> An Holy Person among the Ancients, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of one that had been long stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Glass, fell a VVeeping, and gave this Reason for it, <hi>There's one that has this Morning spent far more time for her Body than I have done for my Soul.</hi> How many <hi>Ladies</hi> would retire from their <hi>Glasses</hi> with VVeeping <hi>Eyes,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their own Account, if their <hi>Eyes</hi> were ever turned <hi>Inward</hi> upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, or <hi>Ʋpward</hi> unto an Angry God, or <hi>Down-ward</hi> unto a Gaping Hell, as they are turned <hi>Awry</hi> to <hi>Behold Vanity!</hi> VVhen a VVoman must be set out with almost as much <hi>Tackling,</hi> as would serve the <hi>Royal Sovereign,</hi> and must be so taken up with Decking a <hi>Body</hi> which is very shortly to feed the VVorms, that her <hi>Soul</hi> which is to live through
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:206531:45"/> Eternal Ages, cannot be well Provided for, she <hi>loses her own Soul,</hi> and yet gains <hi>nothing</hi> of <hi>that,</hi> which if it were <hi>all</hi> gained, would not make up the <hi>loss.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">XI. In times of terrible and general <hi>Calamity,</hi> 'tis fit a VVoman should abridge her self of that Liberty in her <hi>Garb,</hi> which at other times may be allow'd unto her. VVhen the People are in Danger of Ruine, the voice of God unto them is, <hi>Put off your Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> And as for a VVoman to be splendidly Array'd upon a <hi>Day of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation,</hi> is an Affront not only to the <hi>Angels</hi> that see how we look in our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Congregations, but also to the <hi>God</hi> of Angels, before whom we should then appear in what is equivalent unto <hi>Sack-cloth;</hi> so for her ordinarily to glitter with <hi>Costly Array,</hi> at a time when we are peculiarly to <hi>Humble our selves under the mighty hand of God,</hi> is to make her self like that <hi>Midian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tish</hi> Doxy, who had <hi>Zimri</hi> for her Gallant in the Face of the whole Congregation, which were <hi>Weeping before the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">XII. The best <hi>Robes</hi> of any VVo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man are but vile <hi>Rags,</hi> if they either do find her <hi>Destitute</hi> of, or do not make
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:206531:46"/> her <hi>Concerned</hi> for <hi>The Clothing of her Soul.</hi> VVhen <hi>Athanasius</hi> beheld a VVoman gorgeously Attiring of her self, he melted into Tears, <hi>For</hi> (said he) <hi>all this preparation is for her Destruction.</hi> Truly a VVoman is but Equipping her self against <hi>a Day of Slaughter,</hi> if a Bodily Equipage be all that she is furnished with. If she do not <hi>Put on the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ,</hi> what signifies all her <hi>Provision for the Flesh?</hi> If she be not <hi>Array'd in the Fine Linnen clean and white, which is the Righteousness of the Saints.</hi> the <hi>Lamb</hi> of God will disdain to take notice of her. If she have not on <hi>The Wedding Garment,</hi> the King of Heaven will not acknowledge her as a Guest of His. Let her be, <hi>All glorious within,</hi> and from the <hi>Needlework</hi> of the Holy Spirit, Let have an <hi>under garment</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> upon which an <hi>upper garment</hi> of <hi>Glory</hi> shall shortly be induced, or else the Lord will see no <hi>Beauty</hi> in her. If she had no more than a <hi>Peascod</hi> out of which to make her a <hi>Gown</hi> and <hi>Hood,</hi> she would not be so unhappy, as if her Soul go without the <hi>White Rayment,</hi> which the Lord Jesus has Counsell'd her to <hi>Buy</hi> (that is, to <hi>Beg</hi>) of him.</p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:206531:46"/>
                  <p>These are the Lessons, by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance and Observance of which, you may be kept from such <hi>Transgression</hi> in your <hi>Apparrel</hi> as may say, <hi>There is no Fear of God before your Eyes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="counsel">
                  <head>Counsel. 6.</head>
                  <p>But, without your <hi>Faith in Christ,</hi> your <hi>Fear of God,</hi> is utterly to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaired of. No <hi>good Fruit</hi> is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from you, nor do I expect any <hi>good Fruit</hi> of all the perswasives unto the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> now used with you, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less by a <hi>Believing</hi> on, you come to an <hi>Union</hi> with, your Lord Redeemer, who has told you, <hi>without me you can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> Whoever pretends to Write the Calling of a <hi>Vertuous Woman,</hi> and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets to urge <hi>Faith</hi> in the Lord Jesus Christ as the <hi>Root</hi> and <hi>Source</hi> of all true <hi>Virtue,</hi> has finely left out the <hi>One Thing Needful.</hi> There is nothing so <hi>needful</hi> for Women to be advertised of, as a Message like what was carried from the Lord Jesus to that Woman of old, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise, the Master calleth thee!</hi> The <hi>last</hi> thing which therefore is now set before you, is mention'd <hi>last</hi> because 'tis the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:206531:47"/>
                     <hi>first</hi> thing that you are to set upon the practise of; 'Tis <hi>that</hi> of <hi>Believing</hi> on the Lord Jesus Christ; 'tis the answering of the Invitations which that Blessed Lord has given you, <hi>Look unto me that you may be saved,</hi> and <hi>Come unto me that you may have Rest.</hi> We are told in <hi>Heb. 11. 6. Without Faith it is impossible to please God;</hi> and we may therefore say, <hi>without Faith it is impossible to Fear God.</hi> It was when <hi>Faith</hi> in the promised Messiah was work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Heart of our Father <hi>Abraham,</hi> that the Lord said, <hi>Now I know that thou Fearest me.</hi> Those two things are join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Psalmist, in <hi>Psal. 115. 11. Ye that Fear the Lord, Trust in the Lord.</hi> Except we come to a <hi>Trust</hi> in the Lord, for all our Blessedness to be graciously Communicated unto us through the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator. We discover our selves to be without the <hi>Fear</hi> of the Lord; neither shall we ever <hi>grow in Grace,</hi> if we have not a sensible, affecting, fiducial <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Lord Jesus Christ.</hi> O that it may now be said of you, <hi>Woman, great is thy Faith!</hi> and that whereas, <hi>Faith is not of our selves it is the gift of God,</hi> you may beg of <hi>God</hi> this <hi>Gift,</hi> with
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:206531:47"/> a most becoming Importunity, <hi>Lord I would Believe, help my Ʋnbelief.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That you may not want a Descrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that <hi>Faith,</hi> with which you should so apply your selves to the Lord Jesus Christ, as that it may be said of you, <hi>Who is this Leaning upon her Beloved?</hi> Let me distinctly entreat you, to pursue the experience of these two Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  <p>First, Get a <hi>Lively sense</hi> of your own <hi>Spiritual Death,</hi> Sinfulness and Wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness. Behold your selves hunted and haunted by the <hi>Avengers of Sin,</hi> and ready to be Destroy'd if a <hi>Refuge</hi> be not provided for you. When you hear the <hi>Voice</hi> of God, as a <hi>Judge</hi> enquiring after you, let it make you as much <hi>Afraid</hi> as your first Mother in the first Garden was. Take a view of your own <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> as the Word of God has repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented it; and let no Creatures whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever then quiet the <hi>Agonies</hi> thence ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing in your minds. Think on the ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rible Wants and Woes of your Souls; think on the <hi>guilt,</hi> and <hi>filth,</hi> and <hi>slavery</hi> wherein you are perishing every day; think on the ever-burning <hi>Fire,</hi> and of the never dying <hi>Worm,</hi> which you are every
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:206531:48"/> day in danger of going down into; think till you cry out, <hi>Oh Wretched Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that I am! Who shall deliver me?</hi> Let not all the <hi>Pleasures</hi> and <hi>Profits,</hi> and <hi>Honours</hi> of this World allay the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresses which your Souls are now cast into; call 'em all, <hi>Miserable Comforters!</hi> and <hi>Lying Vanities!</hi> and <hi>Physicians of no value!</hi> If Self now offer to procure your <hi>Deliverance,</hi> treat that <hi>Idol</hi> with Contempt, and unspeakable Disdain. As for any <hi>Righteousness</hi> of your own to answer the demands of the <hi>Law,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, <hi>'Tis all filthiness;</hi> as for any <hi>Strength</hi> of your own, to fulfil so much as the Commands of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>I have no Sufficiency!</hi> pronounce your selves Lost, and write your selves, <hi>Wretched and Poor and Miserable, and Blind, and Naked.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Being thus <hi>Humbled,</hi> or having your Security in your Natural Estate so far disturbed, that you feel you must re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all <hi>but</hi> Christ, all <hi>for</hi> Christ, <hi>then</hi> cast your selves upon the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ for all manner of good. Humbly, Hopefully, Joyfully go to him for all the <hi>Sure Mercies</hi> of the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; for all the Benefits whereof
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:206531:48"/>
                     <hi>it has pleased the Father there should in him all fulness dwell;</hi> for all the <hi>Wisdom, Righteousness, Sanctification,</hi> and <hi>Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> which he is to be made unto us. First, <hi>Accept</hi> the Lord Jesus Christ in <hi>His Word.</hi> When you hear the tender of a <hi>Jesus</hi> made unto you, Reply upon it, <hi>Lord, let me have a Jesus upon any Terms!</hi> and like the Dying Martyr say, <hi>None but Christ! None but Christ!</hi> Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der seriously, how the Lord Jesus Christ Executes the Office of a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and of a <hi>Priest,</hi> and of a <hi>King;</hi> and when you are asked, whether you are willing to enjoy the <hi>Instruction</hi> of that <hi>Prophet,</hi> the <hi>Atonement</hi> of that <hi>Priest,</hi> and the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> of that <hi>King,</hi> let your sincere answer be, <hi>Lord, with all my Heart!</hi> And then, <hi>Present</hi> the Lord Jesus Christ, in <hi>your Prayer.</hi> When you make any Request unto the Almighty, let the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> and <hi>Virtue</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ, be the Ground of your Hope to speed in all. The <hi>Mediation</hi> of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, let <hi>that</hi> both Embolden your Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications <hi>to,</hi> and encourage your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations <hi>from,</hi> the God of Heaven. Particularly, when you Pray for the <hi>Favour</hi> of God, let this be your Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:206531:49"/>
                     <hi>The Lord Jesus Christ has made Satisfaction for us by his Obedience, and now he ever lives to make Intercession for us.</hi> When you Pray for any <hi>Counsel</hi> or <hi>Conduct,</hi> Relye upon this, <hi>Ʋnto us a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour is given, whose Name is Wonderful, Counsellour!</hi> When you Pray for any <hi>Succour</hi> or <hi>Supply,</hi> Relye upon this, <hi>There is a Man upon the Throne, by whom all the Wheels in the World are managed!</hi> Oh let the view of a Sweet Jesus cause you to silence all your Dispair of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and say, <hi>Why art thou cast down, O my Soul, Hope in God, since he has provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a Jesus for thee.</hi> This is the <hi>Faith of Gods Elect.</hi> We read in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 6. concerning <hi>Silly Women, Laden with Sins;</hi> Creatures indeed, which do not <hi>feel</hi> their <hi>Load.</hi> But it is the Call of our Lord, in <hi>Mat. 11. 28. Come to me, all ye that are Heavy Laden.</hi> May you find your Souls <hi>Heavy Laden</hi> with a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainous Weight of <hi>Sins</hi> upon you; and may you carry such awakened Souls unto the Lord Jesus, as unto him whom God has <hi>Exalted,</hi> that he may bestow both <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Remission</hi> of Sins up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his <hi>Israel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:206531:49"/>
                  <p>That so the Address now made you, may as well be <hi>Agreeable</hi> as <hi>Effectual,</hi> give me leave to press it, under the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Marriage whereof the Son of God now makes you most Condescend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Overtures. Never were you treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with such an Important and Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Affair, as that which I now chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge your <hi>Earnest</hi> Heed unto; and therefore let the Words once used by a <hi>Woman,</hi> be now with a little Alteration <hi>Mine, Intreat me not to leave thee, or to return from following after thee; for I must prevail with thee to take my God and my Christ, as thine for ever.</hi> The Ministers of the Lord Jesus Christ are called, <hi>The Friends of the Bridegroom;</hi> Now let one of <hi>them</hi> inform you, That the Prince of Life, the Lord of Glory, the King of Heaven, makes unto <hi>you,</hi> even unto sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful worthless <hi>you,</hi> a Motion of a <hi>Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age</hi> with Himself. O do not slight the Motion of such a <hi>Transcendent Match!</hi> but, that I may speak in the Apostles Language, <hi>Let me Espouse you to one Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, that I may present you, as a Chast Virgin to Christ.</hi> We read in <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 6, 7. There is <hi>A Voice as it were of a Great Multitude, and the Voice of Mighty
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:206531:50"/> Thunders, saying, Hallelujah, let us be glad and rejoice for the Marriage of the Lamb is come, and his Wife has made her self Ready!</hi> Could I speak with a <hi>Voice</hi> like that of <hi>Mighty Thunders,</hi> I would now call upon a <hi>Great Multitude</hi> that they would <hi>make themselves ready</hi> for a <hi>Marriage</hi> with the <hi>Lamb</hi> of God. O don't refuse a <hi>Match</hi> with the <hi>Lamb,</hi> lest you incur the <hi>Wrath</hi> of the <hi>Lamb;</hi> or indeed, lest <hi>He</hi> become a <hi>Lion,</hi> and He <hi>Tear you to pieces, while there is none to Deliver.</hi> Methinks, there should not need many Arguments to perswade you unto such a <hi>Marriage</hi> as you now have the Tenders of. If there do, then <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider</hi> the <hi>Necessity</hi> of this Marriage. The Apostle speaking of a Woman, being not married unto another Man in a time of Raging Persecution, says, in 1 <hi>Cor. 7. 40. She is happier if she so abide.</hi> But for a Woman that is not Matried unto the Lord Jesus Christ, wo to her, if <hi>she so abide!</hi> she is horridly undone, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminably and intolerably ruin'd, <hi>if she so abide!</hi> If this be not enough, then <hi>Consider</hi> the <hi>Ʋtility</hi> of this Marriage. When a Woman is Married unto a Neighbour, she is made owner of what
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:206531:50"/> he <hi>is,</hi> and of what he <hi>has;</hi> and a <hi>Beggar</hi> may be made an <hi>Empress</hi> when a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Prince has taken her. But let a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man be Married unto the Lord Jesus Christ, and what follows? 'Tis no less than that in 1 <hi>Cor. 3. 22, 23. All things are yours, and ye are Christs.</hi> Oh! what <hi>unsearchable Riches,</hi> are you made pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently partakers of. If this avail not, <hi>Consider,</hi> then the <hi>Excellency</hi> of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, who Courts you to the Marriage. 'Tis said of Him, in <hi>Cant. 5. 16. He is altogether lovely;</hi> and can't you <hi>Love</hi> such an one? <hi>He</hi> is, <hi>the Desire of all Nations;</hi> and will not you <hi>Desire</hi> Him? <hi>He</hi> is, <hi>The Pearl of great Price;</hi> and will you set no <hi>Price</hi> upon Him? <hi>He</hi> is, <hi>The Christ of God;</hi> and O why should not you say, <hi>Let Him be my Christ for ever?</hi> And if none of all this will break your Hearts, let it be Considered, that it is the Lord Jesus Christ <hi>Himself</hi> who has made the <hi>First Offers</hi> of this <hi>Astonishing Match.</hi> We forlorn Creatures, by the <hi>Hedges</hi> and in the <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ches</hi> of Hell, never durst have dreamt of such an Exaltation, if that Glorious Monarch himself had not made the <hi>First offers</hi> of it; He was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self <hi>Made of a Woman,</hi> on purpose that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:206531:51"/> so he might be <hi>Married</hi> unto the <hi>Children of Men;</hi> and the Souls of <hi>Women</hi> as well as of <hi>Men</hi> are capable of this <hi>Mistical Marriage.</hi> This Illustrious Lord, who is infinitely <hi>Higher than the Kings of the Earth,</hi> does now himself do so strange a thing, as to <hi>Beseech</hi> you, <hi>That you would accept of him as the Husband of your Souls;</hi> and that you would be willing to have an interest in that priviledge, <hi>Thy Maker is thy Husband, and thy Redeemer; The Lord of Hosts is his Name; and thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decmer.</hi> O Heart of Adamant, which these Considerations do not Overcome and Mollify!</p>
                  <p>But it is possible the Women to whom I write, may find their Hearts complying with the Proposals of the Blessed Saviour, when they see those Proposals more distinctly laid before them. It is therefore Desired, First, That you would <hi>Renounce</hi> all other <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi> besides the Lord Jesus Christ. It is the Demind of our Lord Jesus, in <hi>Hos. 3. 3. Thou shalt not play the Harlot, and thou shalt not be for another man, so will I also be for thee.</hi> You have indeed given your <hi>First Loves,</hi> unto the Idols of your Souls; but O where are your
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:206531:51"/>
                     <hi>Wonderments</hi> that the Son of God should not be averse after all, to make you, <hi>His!</hi> Although the <hi>Priest</hi> of old, might not Marry a <hi>Widom;</hi> yet our Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>High Priest,</hi> Jesus, is willing to Marry a Soul that has been fearfully Vitiated and Prostituted; <hi>Thou hast play'd the Harlot with many Lovers, yet return again unto me saith the Lord.</hi> But that which the Lord now expects of you is, to forsake and and shake off, all the old <hi>Oppressours</hi> of your Souls for ever. Unto the <hi>Flesh</hi> now say, <hi>I will not have thy Lusts to be my Laws any more!</hi> Unto the <hi>World</hi> now say, <hi>I will not seek my chief good among thy Vexatious Vanities any more!</hi> And unto the <hi>Devil</hi> say, <hi>I will no more be among thy Slaves, whom thou lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Captive at thy will!</hi> Resolve, that if ever these <hi>Other Lords</hi> do after this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any thing from you, it shall be by the Violence of a <hi>Rape,</hi> which you will never cease <hi>crying</hi> to Heaven for help against. And it is Then, desired that you would <hi>receive</hi> the Lord Jesus Christ, <hi>With</hi> and <hi>For</hi> all <hi>His Mercies. Receive</hi> him with the Wish of your Souls, to be by him <hi>Furnished</hi> and <hi>Provided</hi> with all manner of good, and by him to <hi>bring
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:206531:52"/> forth Fruit</hi> unto him. <hi>Receive</hi> him free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, fully, firmly, hoping to live <hi>on</hi> him, <hi>to</hi> him, and <hi>with</hi> him World without End. Fall down like <hi>Mary</hi> in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den crying out, <hi>Rabboni; O my Lord! my Lord!</hi> With a Transported Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on say unto him, <hi>Lord, be thou mine, make me thine, and let my Jesus be for ever the Beloved of my Soul!</hi> and upon your own Souls lay that charge continually, <hi>Hearken, O Daughter; He is thy Lord, and Worship thou him!</hi> But receive him also very <hi>Thankfully;</hi> for if when the Servants of <hi>David</hi> came to <hi>Abigail,</hi> say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>David sent us unto thee, to take thee to him, to Wife,</hi> 'tis reported in 1 <hi>Sam. 25. 41. She bowed her self on her face to the Earth, and said, Behold, let thine Handmaid, be a Servant, to Wash the Feet of the Servants of my Lord.</hi> Much more, when our Heavenly <hi>David,</hi> sends to Marry your Souls unto himself, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes you, most humbly to cast your selves at <hi>His Feet,</hi> and adore his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness with never ending <hi>Hallellujahs.</hi> It was uttered with some Extasie, by that Woman of Old, <hi>Whence is this to me, that the Mother of my Lord should come to me!</hi> But surely then, you have cause to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:206531:52"/> say with as Rapturous Elevations and Acclamations of your Souls. <hi>O whence is this to me, that my Lord himself, should not only come, but also give himself, to such a Wretch as I am!</hi> In the mean time, let not your want of a <hi>Dowry</hi> discourage you from <hi>receiving</hi> of that Rich Lord, who has infinitely more than <hi>The Earth and the Fulness thereof.</hi> Many a Poor Soul is <hi>Afraid</hi> of receiving the Lord Jesus Christ, because they have nothing to <hi>bring</hi> unto him; they see themselves vile, forlorn, lothsome, and think they, <hi>Will the Glorious Jesus Look upon such an One!</hi> Yes, <hi>that</hi> he will; nor will he look upon any but such as count and feel themselves to be <hi>such:</hi> and can venture to throw themselves into his Arms. notwithstanding their being <hi>so.</hi> You must come to the Lord Jesus, with such Acknowledgements as these; <hi>Lord, if thou Marry me to thy self, I have horrible Doubts upon me, which thou must answer for. I have nothing but Guiltiness, Wretchedness, Ignorance and Slavery, to recommend me to thy favours, that, and some little sense of that, is all that I have to bring unto thy Majesty. With all that, I now cast my self upon thee, and according
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:206531:53"/> to thy Glorious Grace, I must now be thine for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I Pray, that this matter may be brought unto a happy Issue before we part. Reader, <hi>As an Embassador, for Christ, I do in the stead of Christ beseech you,</hi> That you would be <hi>Married</hi> unto that Lord Redeemer. Will you give your <hi>Consent</hi> unto the motion? Give but <hi>that</hi> and the <hi>Match</hi> is made; and so, Blessed you, that ever you were Born? Let your Hearts within you, now an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, <hi>I will,</hi> and you will make this, <hi>The Day of your Espousals,</hi> and <hi>the Day of the Gladness of your Hearts.</hi> Hear the sweet Voice of the Lord Jesus, from the Lofty Battlements of Heaven, this Day calling upon you. His Voice is, <hi>Art thou willing, that my Righteousness, and Satisfaction, and Intercession, be that alone which may purchase for thee all thy Blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness?</hi> Reply, <hi>Lord, I am willing.</hi> His Voice is, <hi>Art thou willing that my Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and my Eye-salve, should lead thee in the way of peace?</hi> Reply, <hi>Lord, I am wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi> His Voice is, <hi>Art thou willing, that I should set up my Kingdom in thee, and strengthen thee against all the Enemies thereof?</hi> Reply, <hi>Lord, I am willing.</hi>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:206531:53"/> Behold. the <hi>Knot</hi> is now ty'd; and it won't be long before the <hi>Consummation</hi> of it, and your <hi>Cohabitation</hi> with the Lord. The Lord Jesus will shortly fetch you away to the <hi>Mansions</hi> in his <hi>Fathers House;</hi> and so you shall <hi>Be for ever with the Lord.</hi> What shall I say more? Let me plead with you like a Servant of my Lord: <hi>If you will deal kindly and truly with my Master, tell me;</hi> Will you go to the Son of God for Life, or no? What is your Answer? Oh! let it be like that which <hi>Rebeckah</hi> made, in <hi>Gen. 24. 42. I will go.</hi> I have only this to tell you, That you'll spend Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Ages in Praising of God for sending this little Book into your hands. If this may be the Result and Effect of your perusing it. But Oh! the incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Torments of that <hi>Wrath,</hi> which is reserved for, <hi>The Children of Ʋnperswade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableness.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I <hi>Therefore now bow my Knees unto thee, O Father of Spirits, That a Day of thy Power may come unto the Reader of these Lines, and that she may be made willing in this Day of thy Power, to give her Self and her Love unto the Eternal Son of thy Love;</hi> AMEN. And let her that
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:206531:54"/> Reads also say, <hi>AMEN</hi> and <hi>AMEN.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="counsel">
                  <head>COƲNSEL. 7.</head>
                  <p>And yet there is this one thing more, which <hi>Women</hi> are to be advised unto; Namely, To maintain, <hi>The Fear of God,</hi> in every condition of Life, into and thorow which the, <hi>will of God</hi> may carry them. There are particularly, <hi>Four States,</hi> in one of which all Women are, and to most of which, perhaps most Women come. Let there be set be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, the portraiture of, <hi>A Virtuous Woman,</hi> in each of those <hi>Four States;</hi> and let it be your study to answer that portraiture by <hi>the Fear of God,</hi> in all. While I manage this Discourse, I shall take the liberty to touch now and then upon the signification of such NAMES as are most usual with the <hi>Female Sex;</hi> partly, because it is a <hi>Curiosity</hi> which you would willingly be entertained with; but cheifly, because I may make some Lessons the more easily remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, yea, and the more thoroughly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by that <hi>Curiosity.</hi> At least I hope, I shall not meet with such an hard Fate, as that German Divine
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:206531:54"/> who telling his Auditory, that <hi>Ʋrsula</hi> signified, <hi>A litttle Bear,</hi> a Woman of that Name caused such an Up-roar a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Women against him, as drove him out of the Town.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The Virtuous MAID.</head>
                     <p>'TIS the wish of the Psalmist, in <hi>Psal. 144. 12. That our Daughters may be as Corner Stones, Polished after the Similitude of a Palace.</hi> The Name of <hi>Pernel,</hi> [or <hi>Petronella</hi>] which signifies, <hi>A pritty little Stone,</hi> has been sometimes put upon a <hi>Daughter.</hi> And now behold, <hi>A Virtuous Daughter</hi> is here styled, <hi>A Polished Corner Stone</hi> by the Spirit of God; She is indeed a <hi>Margaret,</hi> that is to say, <hi>A precious one.</hi> It seems 'tis a thing that more than a little sets off the happiness of a People, when the <hi>Young Women</hi> among them have Accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which render them, like the Tall, Fine, Costly <hi>Pillars,</hi> that are usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at the Gates of <hi>Palaces.</hi> The most <hi>Christian Jew</hi> in his Translation of that place, makes the wish to run, <hi>That our Daughters may be—the Building of the Temple.</hi> And indeed it is no small hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:206531:55"/> unto a People, when the <hi>Young Women</hi> among them, do <hi>Build</hi> the <hi>Temple</hi> of God, and become <hi>Stones</hi> fit for a Room in that <hi>Building.</hi> It has doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less been a most Encouraging thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to some one Gathered <hi>Church</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ, to see about Thirty or Forty Gracious <hi>Young Women,</hi> in two or three years time (as perhaps there have been seen) Addressing them for their Sacred Communion at the Table of the Lord. Now 'tis by, <hi>The Fear of God,</hi> that a Maid may become one of these Happy <hi>Daughters. A Virtuous Maid,</hi> will not Count her self too Youg to be concerned about, <hi>The Fear of God,</hi> but she Obeys that Call, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy Creator in the Days of thy Youth;</hi> She believes that word, <hi>Behold, Now is the accepted Time, Behold, now is the Day of Salvation!</hi> And let us now see what her Carriage is.</p>
                     <p n="1">I. Such is her <hi>Devotion,</hi> that while she <hi>prudently</hi> avoids the Reading of <hi>Romances,</hi> which do no less Naturally than Generally inspire the minds of Young People with <hi>Humours,</hi> that are as <hi>Vicious</hi> as they are <hi>Foolish;</hi> on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side, she <hi>Piously</hi> Reads the Bible
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:206531:55"/> Every Day, and she thence fetches those Humble and Holy, and seriou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Prayers</hi> which do obtain for her, all manner of <hi>Grace to help in a Time of Need.</hi> The Name of <hi>Agatha,</hi> of <hi>A good one,</hi> is that which for this cause pertains unto her; and she is an <hi>Anna,</hi> or an <hi>Hannah,</hi> which is to say, <hi>A gracious one.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">II. Such is her <hi>Purity,</hi> that while she will not suffer the least <hi>Behaviour</hi> or <hi>Expression</hi> to proceed from her, which may Savour of obscaenity; so neither will she <hi>Permit,</hi> much less <hi>Invite,</hi> the Dalliances of any Wanton Creatures which may design any thing besides what is <hi>Honourable</hi> on her; nor will she <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure</hi> to hear any talk that shall not sound innocently, without bestowing the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke of, at least that which for her sake we stile, <hi>A Maiden-Blush</hi> upon it. She is an <hi>Agnes,</hi> that is, <hi>A Chast one.</hi> The Name of <hi>Catharine,</hi> that is, <hi>A Puritan,</hi> agrees well unto her; and she had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have it, though with a scornful Nick-name, than go without it.</p>
                     <p n="3">III. Such is her <hi>Modesty,</hi> that she chooses to be <hi>Seen</hi> rather than <hi>Heard</hi> wherever she comes; And instead of that <hi>Confidence</hi> in <hi>Repartees</hi> and <hi>Railleries</hi>
                        <pb n="98" facs="tcp:206531:56"/> which passes for Good-breeding with a Debauched Generation, or instead of being like those who (as one says) <hi>More Bridle in their Chins, than their Tongues,</hi> she counts <hi>Tace,</hi> which in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish is, <hi>Hold your Peace,</hi> a Name some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times worn by some of her Sex, to be a Rule always to be heeded by her self. But if she be constrained at all to speak, she still is an <hi>Eulalia,</hi> or, <hi>A Well-spoken One;</hi> and though she will not be, <hi>As an Hind let loose,</hi> yet she will ever, <hi>Give Goodly Words.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">IV. Such is her <hi>Industry,</hi> that she be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times applies her self to learn all the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of <hi>Housewifry,</hi> and besides a good skill at her <hi>Needle,</hi> as well as in the <hi>Kitchen,</hi> she acquaints her self with <hi>Arithmetick</hi> and <hi>Accomptanship,</hi> [perhaps also <hi>Chirurgery</hi>] and such other Arts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to <hi>Business,</hi> as may enable her to do the <hi>Man</hi> whom she may hereafter have, <hi>Good and not Evil all the days of her Life.</hi> If she have any Time after this to learn <hi>Musick</hi> and <hi>Language,</hi> she will not loose her Time, and yet she will not be proud of her <hi>Skill;</hi> though the Name of <hi>Lora,</hi> that is, <hi>Learning,</hi> (which the <hi>Saxons</hi> had in use among them for
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:206531:56"/> their Women) should justly belong unto her. She would with all good Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishments be a <hi>Ruth;</hi> which is to say, <hi>A Filled one.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">V, Such is her <hi>Discretion,</hi> that while 'tis too absurdly counted a <hi>Great Curse</hi> to be an <hi>Old Maid,</hi> she makes her <hi>Single</hi> State a <hi>Blessed</hi> one, by improving her <hi>Liesure</hi> from the Encumbrances of a Family, in <hi>Cairing for the Things of the Lord, that she may be Holy both in Body and in Spirit:</hi> And when she sees what Liberty she thereby has, <hi>To serve the Lord without Distraction,</hi> she calls her self a <hi>Beatrice,</hi> that is, <hi>A Blessed Woman.</hi> She does not <hi>Vow</hi> a perpetual Virginity, lest her <hi>Vow</hi> should happen to expose her; while there are <hi>Devils</hi> as well as <hi>Angels,</hi> which do <hi>not Marry, nor are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in Marriage.</hi> But yet instead of using any Hasty Method to get into the <hi>Married Row,</hi> and instead of taking a <hi>Bad</hi> Husband meerly to avoid the little Reproach of having <hi>None,</hi> she do's by her Gravity and Holiness, convince all the World, that her present circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are of <hi>Choice</hi> rather than <hi>Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ce;</hi> and the longer she is in them, the more she do's <hi>Consecrate</hi> her self unto the Lord</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <pb n="100" facs="tcp:206531:57"/>VI. Such is her <hi>Obedience,</hi> that as 'twas none of her manner to seek a Match for her self, by putting her self into a <hi>Flanting Dress,</hi> knowing that such a Dress would make a <hi>Wiseman</hi> afraid of her, and it were better to have no <hi>Husband,</hi> than to have such a <hi>Buzzard</hi> as could be caught by any <hi>Cassandra</hi>'s [or Women that <hi>set Men on fire</hi>] in the Snares of an extravagant Gaity and Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very; so when a Match do's offer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>himself unto her, she wisely leaves it unto the Reasonable Judgment of her Parents or Guardians, whether he be indeed a <hi>Match</hi> for her, or no; nor will she dispose of her self without their Consent, Conduct and Blessing in it. Indeed she reckons this is a proper <hi>Test,</hi> by which a Real and a Worthy <hi>Lover</hi> may be try'd; <hi>Let my Superiors, that have the Disposal of me▪ know your Mind!</hi> so doth she make her self an <hi>Abigail,</hi> or her <hi>Fathers Joy:</hi> and not a <hi>Dinah,</hi> that is, a <hi>Judgment</hi> unto him.</p>
                     <p>This is a Virtuous MAID! And those <hi>Virgins</hi> which are so <hi>Sacred</hi> among the Ancient Romans; as to be made the <hi>Sanctuaries</hi> of the greatest Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, did not more deserve all Respect
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:206531:57"/> and Honour, than the <hi>Virgins</hi> which thus manifest, <hi>The Fear of God.</hi> But we hope it will not be long before she becomes a WIFE; which will render her a <hi>Mary,</hi> that is, an <hi>Exalted</hi> one; and let us now see, what a <hi>Virtuous</hi> one.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The Virtuous WIFE.</head>
                     <p>VVHEN Mr. <hi>William Whately,</hi> was going to Publish a Book which insisted much on the Duties of a <hi>Wife,</hi> he Dedicated the Book to his Father-in-law; and in the Epistle, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Solemn Thanks unto him for his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowing on him, <hi>A most Excellent and Virtuous Wife,</hi> he adds; <hi>I have been the better able to show, what a Good Wife should be, by finding the full Duty of a Wife con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually performed unto me, in my own House; most easily therefore might I set out a Picture of that</hi> (says he) <hi>which is hourly conversant before my Eyes.</hi> I cannot say that I am <hi>any farther;</hi> but I have cause to render unto Heaven my daily and Hearty Thanks, that I am <hi>thus far,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantaged for my describing of <hi>A Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Wife;</hi> and if I thus Publish this
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:206531:58"/> Mercy of God unto my self, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthiest of Men, let me not be Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured as if my <hi>Freedom</hi> were a <hi>Folly;</hi> not only because those Eminent Persons <hi>Budaeus</hi> and <hi>Paraeus</hi> have before me, in Print Celebrated each of them the worth of his <hi>Virtuous Wife,</hi> but also be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the <hi>Wise</hi> Man reckons it among the priviledges of a <hi>Virtuous Wife,</hi> in <hi>Prov. 31. 28. Her Husband also, he Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth her.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It was a great abuse which the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents who doted upon <hi>Virginity,</hi> put upon those words of the Apostle, in <hi>Rom. 8. 8. Those that are in the Flesh cannot please God;</hi> when they supposed all <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Persons</hi> to be those intended. A <hi>Virtuous Wife</hi> is one that <hi>pleaseth God,</hi> as much as if she were cloistered up in the strictest and closest <hi>Nunery;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, yea, therein she pleaseth a <hi>Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Husband</hi> also; she studies to render her self a true <hi>Mabel,</hi> or <hi>Amiable</hi> person, in his Eyes; and a Right <hi>Evodias,</hi> or, One <hi>of a Good Savour</hi> to him. You shall now hear her Qualities.</p>
                     <p n="1">I. As for her <hi>Love</hi> to her Husband, I may say, <hi>'Tis even strong as Death, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:206531:58"/> waters cannot quench it. neither can the Floods drown it.</hi> She can like <hi>Sarah, Rebeckah, Rachel,</hi> freely leave all the Friends in the World for his Company; and she looks upon that charge of God unto his Ministers, <hi>Teach the Young Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to Love their Husbands,</hi> as no less profitable, than highly reasonable. When she reads that Prince <hi>Edward</hi> in his Wars against the <hi>Turks,</hi> being stab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with a poisoned Knife, his Princess did suck the poison out of his Wounds with her own Royel <hi>Mouth;</hi> she finds in her own Heart a principle disposing her to show her own Husband as great a <hi>Love.</hi> When she reads of a Woman called <hi>Herpine,</hi> who having her Husband Appoplex'd in all his Limbs, bore him on her back a Thousand and three Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred English Miles to a Bath, for his Recovery; she finds her self not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unwilling to have done the like. When she reads of those famous Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who after a hot Siege in the Castle of <hi>Winsberg,</hi> having obtained this liberty from therir enraged Enemies, <hi>That they might themselves go out, and also take any one thing they could carry with them;</hi> very bravely took up each one her Husband.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:206531:59"/> and so delivered them: She applauds the Example and would follow it. And when she reads of that Generous Young Woman, <hi>Clara Cerventa,</hi> who having for her Husband one <hi>Valdaura,</hi> that prov'd full of most loathsome <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases,</hi> yet she tended him with all the care and cost imaginable, and sold her Jewels to maintain him; and at his Death, after ten long years of Languish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, she reply'd unto her Friends who would rather have Congratulated her Deliverance, <hi>That she would freely lose the best of her Enjoyments to purchase her Dear</hi> Valdaura <hi>again!</hi> She resolves the <hi>Imitation</hi> of such a Carriage, while she bestows an <hi>Admiration</hi> on it. Her <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections</hi> were not at first founded on the <hi>Estate</hi> or <hi>Beauty</hi> of her Husband; and therefore <hi>These</hi> happen to be consumed, <hi>Those</hi> do out-live their Funeral, 'Tis her <hi>Piety</hi> towards the Commandment and Ordinance of God, that Inspires her Affections; and so they do not grow cold like a Smiths red hot <hi>Bar of Iron,</hi> when taken out from the <hi>Fire</hi> of a misplaced <hi>Lust.</hi> When she addresses him, with such a Compellation, as,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:206531:59"/> LOVE, her <hi>Heart</hi> goes with her <hi>Lips,</hi> and she <hi>means</hi> what she <hi>speaks.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">II. But her <hi>Love</hi> to her Husband, will also admit, yea, and Produce the <hi>Fear</hi> of, <hi>A Cautious Diligence never to Displease him.</hi> 'Twas this which the Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> meant when he recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends unto the Women, <hi>A Chast Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation Coupled with Fear;</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> when he requires of the Woman, <hi>To Reverence her Husband.</hi> While she looks upon him as <hi>Her Guide,</hi> by the constitution of God, she will not Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with <hi>Sarah</hi> to call him <hi>Her Lord;</hi> and though she do's not <hi>Fear</hi> his <hi>Blowes,</hi> yet she do's <hi>Fear</hi> his <hi>Frowns,</hi> being loth in any way to grieve him, or cause an <hi>Head-ake</hi> in the Family by offending him. She would have that famous <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the Persians</hi> mentioned in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Bible, <hi>That all the Wives give to their Husbands Honour, both to great and small;</hi> to be as a <hi>Law of the Persians,</hi> altogether <hi>Ʋnalterable.</hi> In every <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> thing she submits her <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Sense</hi> to his, where she cannot with calm <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> convince him of <hi>Inexpediencies;</hi> and instead of grudging or captious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, she acts as if there were but
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:206531:60"/>
                        <hi>One Mind in two Bodies.</hi> If her <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> give order, <hi>Make ready quickly three Measures of Meal</hi> or the like, 'tis as quickly done; If her <hi>Jacob</hi> say to her, <hi>I must have you go with me,</hi> she most rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily yields unto him. If his <hi>Ʋnreason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Humours</hi> happen to be such, that she must give some diversion to them▪ she remembers that Rule, <hi>In her Tongue is the Law of Kindness;</hi> 'tis by the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, the sweetness, the goodness of her expressions that she gives <hi>Law</hi> unto him. If she speaks of him, 'tis not in such Terms as the <hi>Harlot</hi> uses in <hi>Proverbs, The Man;</hi> but it is with all manner of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect: She will not <hi>Blaze</hi> any Infirmity of his, nor will she <hi>Blast</hi> his Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; being indeed sensible that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Ignominy she cast upon him, it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly <hi>Rebounds</hi> and <hi>Redounds</hi> upon her self: Here she is a true <hi>Milea,</hi> that is, <hi>A Woman of Counsel.</hi> If she speak to him, 'tis not with Talkative and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handsome <hi>Interruptions,</hi> nor with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mis-becoming <hi>Insolencies;</hi> though he be never so much a <hi>Churl,</hi> yet she e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver treats him with the Language of an <hi>Abigail.</hi> Though she be a <hi>Sarah,</hi> that is, a <hi>Mistriss;</hi> yet she owns that she
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:206531:60"/> has a <hi>Master:</hi> And like a <hi>Sarah</hi> of old, she will not so much as take in, or cast out a <hi>Servant</hi> without Consulting <hi>Him;</hi> nor will she receive any <hi>Guests</hi> or <hi>Goods</hi> into her House, unless like the <hi>Shunamite,</hi> she may have her Husbands Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and she will have at least some <hi>Implicit</hi> or <hi>General</hi> Consent of <hi>His,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore she will exercise any <hi>Secret Bounties</hi> with his Possessions. His <hi>Anger</hi> will not cause her to swallow a <hi>Reproof</hi> with discontent, and his <hi>Foundness</hi> will not make her to forget the <hi>Honour</hi> that she owes unto him. Indeed there is a Store of <hi>Michols</hi> in the World; <hi>Michol,</hi> is as much as to say, <hi>Who is all</hi> (in the House) <hi>but She?</hi> But let us leave it unto such <hi>Michols</hi> alone, <hi>To despise their Husbands in their Hearts;</hi> God will punish them.</p>
                     <p n="3">III. But her <hi>Fear</hi> of Displeasing her Husband, most remarkably appears in the <hi>Peace</hi> that she preserves with him; and her <hi>Antipathy</hi> to all <hi>Contention,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less it be that of <hi>Provoking one another to Love and Good works.</hi> A <hi>Susan</hi> she is, that is, <hi>A Lilly;</hi> but never <hi>A Briar</hi> to him: Nor will she give him cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e to call her <hi>Barbara.</hi> She will have no
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:206531:61"/> such <hi>Passion</hi> towards her Husband as may make her worthy to be called, <hi>A Fury;</hi> but if he be himself in a <hi>Passion,</hi> she strives with the <hi>Soft Answers</hi> of <hi>Meekness</hi> to mollifie it first, and so to overcome it: She is a true <hi>Rachel,</hi> that is to say, <hi>A Sheep</hi> under the greatest Exasperations. A Reverend Person seeing once a Couple that were very Cholerick, yet live most lovingly and peaceably together, demanded of them <hi>Whence it was?</hi> And the man made him this Answer, <hi>Sir, When my Wife is in a Passion I yield unto her; and when I am in a Passion she yields unto me; so that we never are in our passionate fits together!</hi> The Good Woman will make it her endeavour to attend the last part of this Contrivance; and will give small or no occasion for the first. The Marriners Counts it <hi>Bodes well</hi> to see <hi>Two Fire-Balls</hi> appearing in a Ship together; but our Good Woman counts <hi>Two Fire-Balls</hi> in an <hi>House</hi> together, to <hi>Bode ill</hi> as the worst of Omens; nor will she be a party to maintain a <hi>Civil War</hi> within the Walls of her Dwelling. She thinks that if there be nothing but <hi>Fire! Fire!</hi> in the House, 'tis a sign that God, who
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:206531:61"/> is <hi>The God of Peace,</hi> is not graciously present there; as the Jewish Rabbins have noted upon the Hebrew Names of <hi>Ish,</hi> an Husband, and <hi>Ishah</hi> a Wife; out of which if you take the two Letters which make the Name of <hi>Jah,</hi> there will remain only <hi>Esh, Esh,</hi> that is, <hi>Fire! Fire!</hi> The old Heathen took <hi>Gall</hi> from the Nuptial Sacrifices and threw it behind the Altar, to intimate that all <hi>Bitterness</hi> is to be thrown away by all Married People; <hi>Mercury,</hi> or good Language, is to stand by <hi>Venus.</hi> And this Woman accordingly, puts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <hi>All Bitterness, Anger, Clamour, and Evil speaking;</hi> She is a Right <hi>Rebeckah,</hi> which carries <hi>The blunting or hindring of Contention</hi> in the signification of it; and a right <hi>Shelomith,</hi> which is to say, <hi>A Peaceable one.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">IV. But she is for <hi>Plenty</hi> as well as <hi>Peace</hi> in her Houshold; and by her <hi>Thriftiness</hi> makes an Effectual and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Reply unto her Husband. when he does ask her, as he must, <hi>Whether he shall Thrive or no?</hi> She is a <hi>Deborah,</hi> that is, <hi>A Bee</hi> for her Diligence and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry in her <hi>Hive.</hi> As on the one side she will have none in her House to <hi>Want,</hi>
                        <pb n="110" facs="tcp:206531:62"/> so on the other side, she will have all of them to <hi>Work;</hi> or as the Holy Spirit of God expresses it, <hi>She looks well to the ways of her Houshold, and Eats not the Bread of Idleness.</hi> Her Husbands <hi>Gains</hi> are so managed by her Housewifry and Providence, that he finds it his advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to let her keep the <hi>Keys</hi> of all; and she will so regulate all the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mestick Expences, that he shall not complain of <hi>Any thing Embezzled.</hi> Her very <hi>Fore-cast</hi> is as useful as much of her Husbands <hi>Business;</hi> and the Pennies that she saves do add unto the heaps of the Pounds that are got by him. He has a rich <hi>Portion</hi> with her, meerly in her <hi>Prudence;</hi> that is it which renders <hi>her</hi> a <hi>Jerusha,</hi> or an <hi>Inheritance</hi> unto him. She is particularly careful, that she do not bear such a Sail of <hi>Gallantry,</hi> either in her <hi>Table</hi> or <hi>Apparel,</hi> or her <hi>Furniture</hi> as may sink her Husband; nor will she be one of those Women, who (as one says) are <hi>now such skilful Chymists, that they quickly turn their Husbands Earth into Gold; only they pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>sue the Experiment too far, making that Gold too volatile, and let it all Vapour away in insignificant, though Gaudy Trifles.</hi> That Woman
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:206531:62"/> deserves the Name of <hi>Dalilah.</hi> that is, <hi>Povert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>;</hi> [unless you will enter upon so hard a Name as <hi>Jezabel,</hi> that is, <hi>A wo to the House;</hi>] whose <hi>Discretion</hi> shall not be better than a <hi>Dowry</hi> to her Owner.</p>
                     <p n="6">VI. And this <hi>Thriftiness</hi> is accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd with such a <hi>Fidelity</hi> to her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, as that she will not give a <hi>Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> to the least stragling or wandring <hi>Thought</hi> of Disloyalty in his <hi>Bed;</hi> lest by her parling with wicked <hi>Thoughts,</hi> the Devil should insensibly decoy her to the <hi>Deeds</hi> which <hi>God will Judge.</hi> She is a <hi>Dove,</hi> that will sooner die than leave her <hi>Mate;</hi> and her Husband is to her, <hi>The covering of her Eyes,</hi> at such a rate, that she sees a <hi>Desireableness</hi> in him, which she will not allow her self to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold or suppose in <hi>any other;</hi> neither will she look upon <hi>Another,</hi> any more than the Wife of <hi>Tygranes,</hi> who after the Wedding of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> whom every one did commend as the rarest Person in the Company; being by her Huband ask'd <hi>What she thought of him?</hi> Answered roundly, <hi>In truth I looked at no Body there, but you, my Husband.</hi> A Wanton had as good <hi>Eat Fire,</hi> as go to Enkindle any
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:206531:63"/>
                        <hi>False Fire,</hi> or <hi>Fools Fire</hi> in her Holy Breast; she accounts <hi>Adultery</hi> to be as the Law of <hi>Moses</hi> adjudged it, <hi>A Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Crime;</hi> and if the <hi>Egyptians</hi> of old cut off the Nose of the <hi>Adulteress,</hi> or, if the <hi>Athenians</hi> tore her in pieces with wild Horses, rather had she undergo the <hi>Pain</hi> of such things than commit the <hi>Crime.</hi> She is a <hi>Gertude,</hi> or <hi>All true,</hi> in the Marriage Covenant. Yea, she will even <hi>Abstain from all appearance of Evil;</hi> and as 'tis abominable unto her to entertain the least groundless and causless <hi>Jealousie</hi> of her Husband, or to Torture and Expose her own Soul by the uneasie Frenzy of uncharitable sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mizes concerning him; so she will not give <hi>him</hi> the least opportunity to think hardly of her. She will not therefore be too much <hi>from Home,</hi> upon concerns, that perhaps to him are <hi>Ʋnaccountable:</hi> But if the Angels do Enquire, where she is, her Husband may reply as once <hi>Abraham</hi> did, <hi>My Wife is in the Tent.</hi> Although her Husband be not such an <hi>Egyptian</hi> as to deny her <hi>Shoes;</hi> yet her usage of them is, as if like a <hi>Scythian,</hi> she had the <hi>Axle-tree</hi> of the Chariot which carried her home after her Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:206531:63"/> burned at the Door; and she is willing to be painted as the Wives of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Ancients were, with a <hi>Snail</hi> under her Feet. She affects to be an <hi>Esther,</hi> that is, <hi>An Hidden One.</hi> But if a foolish and froward Husband will wrong her with unjust suspicions of her <hi>Hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>sty▪,</hi> she will thence make a Devout Reflexion upon her <hi>Disloyalty</hi> to God; but at the same time very pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently vindicates her <hi>Innocency</hi> to man: And the more patiently, because the <hi>Water of Jealousie</hi> procures greater Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings to those that have it Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously and Abusively Imposed upon them.</p>
                     <p>VI. But her <hi>Fidelity</hi> is no where more signalized, than in her Sollicitude for the <hi>Eternal Salvation</hi> of her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. O how unwilling she is that the Precious and Immortal Soul of her poor Husband, should go from her Arms, to make his <hi>Bed among the Dragons of the Wilderness for ever!</hi> The Apostles Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, <hi>What knowest thou O Wife, but thou mayest save thy Husband?</hi> Is her Apprecation, <hi>O that I may! Chrisostoms</hi> note upon it is, <hi>That the Wife is to remind her Husband of what was delivered in the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:206531:64"/> Church.</hi> Truly, though a Woman may not <hi>Speak in the Church,</hi> yet she may humbly Repeat unto her Husband at <hi>Home</hi> what the Minister <hi>Spoke in the Church,</hi> that may be Pertinent to his condition. Thus every <hi>Paul</hi> may have <hi>Women that labour with him in the Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>pel.</hi> Vast Opportunities are those that a Woman <hi>has</hi> to bring over her Husband unto real and serious Godliness. And a Good Woman will <hi>Ʋse</hi> those Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities. An <hi>Esther,</hi> a Witty <hi>Esther,</hi> what can't she do with the most haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Husband in the World? Wat may not a Godly <hi>Domitia,</hi> or a Godly <hi>Monica</hi> do, for the Souls of their Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Husbands? If her Husband be a Carnal, Prayerless, Graceless man; she will not leave off her Ingenious Perswasions, till it may be said of him, <hi>Behold he I rays!</hi> If her Husband be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Power of any Temptation, she will do what she can to prevent his <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction,</hi> as that famous Woman did for the City of <hi>Abel.</hi> She would merit the Name of an <hi>Eunice,</hi> that is, <hi>A good Conquerer,</hi> by <hi>Conquering</hi> of her Husband unto the liking of all that is <hi>Good.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of saying to him, <hi>Curse God?</hi> She
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:206531:64"/> pursues him with Loving, Winning, Unwearied Sollicitations to <hi>Fear God,</hi> and <hi>Serve God,</hi> and <hi>Never be weary of well doing.</hi> Instead of being a <hi>Dalilah,</hi> that shall entangle him in the Cords of Death, she do's all she can to be a <hi>Pris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilla,</hi> that shall <hi>more fully aquaint him with the Things Pertaning to the Kingdom of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This is a Virtuous WIFE! And such an one she will be, although her Husband should be very disobliging to her; She considers, <hi>'Tis to the Lord</hi> I confess the difficulties that some <hi>Ʋn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Wives</hi> do meet withal, are such that if they be not very <hi>Virtuous Wives</hi> they cannot possibly conform to these Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections; but this I would say, their being <hi>Virtuous</hi> is the most likely way to provide against their being <hi>Ʋnhappy.</hi> But if the Case of any such Wife should be so remarkably hard, that her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band proceeds to abuse her with a <hi>Cudgel</hi> [an <hi>Hard Case</hi> indeed! that a <hi>Brides Bush</hi> ever should have any <hi>Cudgels</hi> growing in it!] I know not what fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Advice to give her: Only THIS; Let the Candidness of her Behaviour be her <hi>Charm</hi> against the Assaults of such a
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:206531:65"/>
                        <hi>Devil;</hi> and if that would further help to lay such a <hi>Friend,</hi> I am content she should Read unto him, not only the <hi>Laws</hi> of God and Man against that Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barity, or the Opinion of old <hi>Cato That for a man to beat his Wife, was as bad as Sacriledge;</hi> but also the Emphatical Words of the Blessed Ancients in the Church of God, Loudly Thundring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this Inhumanity; and particularly those of the Renowned <hi>Chrysostom,</hi> which are to this Purpose; (if you will allow <hi>me</hi> the Translating of them) <q rend="margQuotes">It is the highest <hi>Ignominy,</hi> not of the <hi>Wife,</hi> but of the <hi>Man,</hi> for a <hi>Man</hi> to beat his <hi>Wife.</hi> But if thou hast an Husband that will do so, bear it pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently; and know thou shalt have <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> hereafter for it, as well as <hi>Praises</hi> here. As for You, <hi>Man,</hi> Let me admonish you, that there is no Fault so great, as may compel you to to beat your <hi>Wives.</hi> Your <hi>Wives</hi> did I say? 'Tis a Dishonour for a <hi>Man</hi> to bestow blows upon his <hi>Maid;</hi> and much more upon his <hi>Wife</hi>—We might learn this from the <hi>Law-givers</hi> among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who take away a <hi>Wife</hi> from the <hi>Man</hi> that has beaten
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:206531:65"/> her, for indeed he is a Man unworthy of a <hi>Wife.</hi> Such a <hi>Man,</hi> if he may be call'd a <hi>Man,</hi> and not rather a Beast, is to be counted a Murderer of his <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Mother.</hi> If a Man must leave his <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Mother</hi> for the sake of his <hi>Wife,</hi> by the Ordinance of God; what a mad wretch is he that shall abuse <hi>Her,</hi> for whom his very <hi>Parents</hi> were to be forsaken? Indeed there is not a simple <hi>Frenzy</hi> in this thing; an <hi>Intollerable Disgrace</hi> do's al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so accompany it. At the Sighs and Cries of the Abused <hi>Wife,</hi> all the Neighbourhood run to the Base Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows House, as for the rescue of a Prey fallen into the Talons of a <hi>Wild-Beast</hi> that had broken in. And such a Rascal were better be <hi>Buried alive,</hi> than show his Head among his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours any more. <hi>
                              <bibl>See Hom. l. 26. in 1 Ep. ad Corinth.</bibl>
                           </hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>But wishing all Good Women, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from such Monsters of Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, we will suppose our <hi>Virtuous Wife</hi> now grown a <hi>Mother;</hi> and see how she acquits her self.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:206531:66"/>
                     <head>The Virtuous MOTHER.</head>
                     <p>THE Apostle Wills, <hi>That the Younger Women Marry, and Bear Children;</hi> and as 'tis too soon for them to <hi>Bear Children</hi> till they <hi>Marry,</hi> so 'tis ordinarily expected, that they will <hi>Bear Children</hi> when they <hi>Marry.</hi> If a <hi>Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Wife</hi> be deny'd the blessing of <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> her <hi>not Bearing</hi> is not a Trial that she cannot <hi>Bear.</hi> She humbly addresses the God of Heaven, like <hi>Hanah,</hi> for that Gracious and Powerful <hi>Word</hi> of his which makes Fruitful, as remembring, That <hi>Children are an Heritage of the Lord, and the Fruitful Womb is his Reward;</hi> But she will not impatiently long like <hi>Rachel, Give me Children or I die,</hi> lest she <hi>die</hi> by her having of those <hi>Children.</hi> Much less, will she have so little Wit as to suspect her own <hi>Eternal Happiness,</hi> because of her <hi>Natural Barrenness,</hi> like those mistaken little Women who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thus argued from that Scripture, <hi>She shall be saved in Child bearing;</hi> Very fine indeed! As if <hi>Child-bearing</hi> were no less a condition in the Covenant of Grace, than <hi>Repenting</hi> and <hi>Believing!</hi>
                        <pb n="119" facs="tcp:206531:66"/> But her <hi>Natural Barrenness</hi> is rather im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd by her as an occasion of her <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Happiness,</hi> by the <hi>Spiritual Fulness</hi> whereto she is thereby excited and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted; it causes her to be more <hi>Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he good works of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Charity;</hi> more <hi>Fruitful</hi> in her endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours otherwise to <hi>Serve her Generation after the will of God;</hi> more <hi>Fruitful</hi> in all these things whereby, <hi>The Heavenly Father may be Glorified:</hi> And she will consider with her self, <hi>What Service of God, and his People, and my own Soul have I now a Leisure for?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Nevertheless if our <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> become a Parent, we shall see what a <hi>Virtuous Mother</hi> she will approve her self.</p>
                     <p n="1">I. She is no sooner sensible that she has <hi>Conceivrd,</hi> but she presently and so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly, and perhaps with <hi>Fasting</hi> as well as <hi>Prayer,</hi> applies her self to the God of Heaven, that he would with his own Holy Spirit <hi>Fill</hi> and <hi>Shape</hi> what is in her; and that what is to be Born of her, may be <hi>An Holy Thing.</hi> She ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts the <hi>Treasure</hi> now lodged in her to be of more account than all the Riches of a Thousand <hi>India</hi>'s, inasmuch as 'tis a
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:206531:67"/> Never dying Soul, by which the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God may for ever be Glorify'd. And as therefore she carefully avoids all that may prejudice the Formation of the <hi>Infant</hi> in her, so she loves it afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand with a due <hi>Earliness</hi> and <hi>Earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> that the <hi>Infant</hi> may be <hi>Sanctified in the Womb.</hi> She is not inordinately set upon having an Infant of one Sex, more than another; but her great concern is that which a <hi>Big-bellied</hi> Woman once recorded in a Legacy left written as her Desire for her Unborn Infant, <hi>That she may be a Mother to one of Gods Children!</hi> Suppose it be a <hi>Daughter,</hi> which usually (and perhaps needlesly) is less long'd for; yet if it may be a <hi>Bethia,</hi> that is, <hi>A Daughter of the Lord;</hi> or a <hi>Diana,</hi> that is, <hi>A Diughter of God,</hi> she has her Choice; and she is freely willing that God should have the <hi>Proporti ning</hi> of Sexes in the World.</p>
                     <p n="2">II. That she may be <hi>Saved in Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing, She continues in Faith, and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Holiness, with Sobriety,</hi> all the Months of her Time; and puts her <hi>Husband</hi> also upon the exercise of those Virtues, that it may not only be [<hi>She</hi>] but [<hi>They</hi>] that so <hi>Continues.</hi> By
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:206531:67"/>
                        <hi>Faith</hi> she relies upon the Lord Jesus Christ, who was <hi>Born of a Woman,</hi> for the Salvation both of her Soul and of her Babe, if God should not permit her to out-live the Dangerous Agonies of her Travails: By <hi>Faith</hi> she depends upon the <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Wisdom,</hi> and <hi>Goodness</hi> of God, for her seasonable Deliverance. Like <hi>Sarah, Judging him Faithful who has promised.</hi> The <hi>Burden</hi> which is in her, she does by <hi>Faith</hi> Transfer into the Omnipotent hands of that God, whose invitation to her is, <hi>Cast thy Burden on the Lord;</hi> and she searches the <hi>Bible,</hi> especially the <hi>Psalter,</hi> for words to plead with the Lord upon this great Affair: That word particularly is a sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port unto hee, <hi>Isa. 41. 10. Fear thou not, for I am with thee; Be not dismay'd, for I am thy God; I will strengthen thee, yea, I will help thee, yea, I will uphold thee with the Right Hand of my Righteousness;</hi> and that word in <hi>Psal.</hi> 34. 22. and that in <hi>Psal.</hi> 37. 5. and that in <hi>Psal.</hi> 42. 11. and that in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 13. and that in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 9. and that in <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 5. And her <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Faithfulness</hi> to her Consort, is at the same time such as do's <hi>Adotn the Doctrine of God her Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi>
                        <pb n="122" facs="tcp:206531:68"/> By <hi>Charity</hi> she professes to the Lord Jesus Christ, <hi>Thou knowest that I love thee;</hi> and she can say as that Martyr, who unto the Persecutors that threatned they would berave her of the Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her Life, answered, <hi>Christ is my Husband, you can't strip me of him!</hi> By <hi>Charity</hi> she <hi>Loves the Brethren,</hi> and by suitable kindnesses engages them that have an interest in Heaven, to <hi>Pray</hi> for Prosperity. The <hi>Sacred Fire of her Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> flames especially towards the <hi>Man of her Desires,</hi> whom she <hi>Loves with a pure Heart servently;</hi> and this <hi>Charity</hi> helps her <hi>To endure all things. Her Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness</hi> causes her to Dedicate all that she <hi>has</hi> as well as all that she <hi>is,</hi> unto the Service of God; her <hi>Holiness</hi> makes her spend her time in much Devotion, and use all manner of <hi>Exactness</hi> and <hi>Watchfulness</hi> over all her ways; her <hi>Holiness</hi> dispoles her to be ready for whatever Event the Sovereign God may order for her; and so Ready, that she can without amazement <hi>Lay by the Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen</hi> wherein she would be <hi>Laid out,</hi> in case like <hi>Rache!</hi> she have such <hi>Hard La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> that her <hi>Soul Depart.</hi> Her <hi>Sobriety</hi> renders her a true <hi>Sophronia,</hi> and causes
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:206531:68"/> her with <hi>Modesty</hi> to govern all her <hi>Speeches</hi> and <hi>Passions;</hi> with Temperance like <hi>Manoahs</hi> Wife, to forbear noxious excesses in <hi>Eating</hi> or <hi>Drinking;</hi> and with <hi>Chastity</hi> to Mortifie all inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions unto whatever shall be Loose, Lewd, Lascivious. Being thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Hour, when <hi>The Anguish of bringing forth her Child is upon her,</hi> she is then found composing her self with hope in God; and resolving <hi>Lord, at what Time I am afraid, I will put my Trust in thee!</hi> Indeed the blessed <hi>Sabina,</hi> crying out when she Travelled in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and being asked, <hi>How she would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the Torments and Burnings which her Enemies had prepared for her?</hi> Answered, <hi>I now bear the punishment of my Sin; I shall then suffer Martyrdom for my Saviour.</hi> But a pregnant Christian will moderate her <hi>Complaints</hi> in the Hour, when Pangs take hold on her, because <hi>They have been brought by Sin,</hi> and because, <hi>There is a Saviour who thus came into the World.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">III. When she is well Delivered, she is a true <hi>Judith</hi> or a <hi>Praising</hi> One; Oh! how is that Thankful Question imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately working in her Breast, <hi>What shall
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:206531:69"/> I render to the Lord for all his benefits?</hi> When she finds her self strong enough to Hear and Think, she make<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>The hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Sixteenth Psalm</hi> to be Read un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her; and when she Contemplates what a Million of Mercies there are in the Birth of one <hi>Perfect Child,</hi> she would, if it were <hi>Proper,</hi> Name every one <hi>Mehetabel,</hi> that is, <hi>How good is God!</hi> However she now Devotes her Child unto God, saying with <hi>Hannah, I have lent it unto the Lord as long as it Lives;</hi> even every Daughter shall be a <hi>Bathsheba,</hi> that is, <hi>A Daughter of an Oath,</hi> to God, that so she may be a <hi>Bathshua,</hi> that is, <hi>A Daughter of Salvation</hi> from the Lord. And she desires the <hi>Baptism</hi> of it, not as the Formality of putting a <hi>Name</hi> upon it, nor as an opportunity for <hi>Dressing</hi> and <hi>Showing</hi> of it, but that thus <hi>Coming into the Bond of the Covenant,</hi> it may <hi>Pass under</hi> the Lords Tything <hi>Rod,</hi> as a <hi>Lamb</hi> set a part for him. And how Ardent are her <hi>Groan's</hi> as if she were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>Travelling in Birth again,</hi> that her Child may be washed in the <hi>Laver</hi> of the <hi>New Birth</hi> betimes!</p>
                     <p n="4">IV. Her care for the <hi>Bodies</hi> of her Children, shows it self in her <hi>Nursing</hi> of
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:206531:69"/> them her self, if God have made her <hi>Able</hi> for it, and it <hi>Easie</hi> for her. She is not a <hi>Dame</hi> that shall scorn to Nourish in the <hi>World,</hi> the Children whom she has already Nourish'd in her <hi>Womb:</hi> If like <hi>Sarah</hi> she be a <hi>Lady,</hi> yet she counts it not below her to be a <hi>Nurse.</hi> If God have granted her Bottles of <hi>Milk</hi> on her Breast, she thinks that her Children have a Claim unto them. It shall not be her <hi>Niceness,</hi> but her <hi>Necessity</hi> and <hi>Calamity,</hi> if she do not Suckle her own Off-Spring; and she will not from <hi>Sloth</hi> and <hi>Pride,</hi> be so Unnatural as to give Cause for that Exclamation. <hi>The Sea Monsters draw out the Breast, they give suck to their Young ones; But the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of my People is become Cruel, like the Ostrich in the Wilderness, who is hardened against her Young ones, as though they were not hers.</hi> Now having Nurs'd her Young ones, 'tis her next care that they be well provided, as with such <hi>Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies</hi> as belong to their present state, so with such <hi>Callings</hi> and <hi>Portions</hi> as may hereafter make them serviceable in their Generation; and when they are grown <hi>Marriageable,</hi> her Discretion and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:206531:70"/> her Tenderness is yet more Eminently seen in her Matching of them.</p>
                     <p n="5">V. But her <hi>Zeal</hi> for the <hi>Spirits</hi> of her Children, is that which do's most <hi>Eat her up;</hi> O how concerned she is, that they may be <hi>Brought up in the Nurture and Admonition of the Lord!</hi> When she first received her Children, she imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Immortal God committing them to her charge, as the Princess of <hi>Egypt</hi> unto the Mother of <hi>Moses, Here, Take this Child, Nurse it for me, and I'll give thee thy Wages.</hi> Wherefore she be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a <hi>Martha,</hi> that is, <hi>A Teacher,</hi> to them all. She begins with them while they are upon her <hi>Knees,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structs them how to fall down in <hi>Prayer</hi> upon their own. She will not put them upon <hi>Revenge,</hi> by asking them to give her a <hi>Blow</hi> that she may <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>tt</hi> any thing that vexes them; but she fears they will soon Learn <hi>That,</hi> and every other Vice without a <hi>Teacher.</hi> The <hi>First Liquors</hi> that she puts into those <hi>Little Vessels,</hi> are Histories and Sentences fetch'd from the Oracles of God, and and Institutions <hi>How to Pray in Secret un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Heavenly Father.</hi> She then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to make 'em Expert in some <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:206531:70"/> Catechisms,</hi> and will have 'em Learn to <hi>Read</hi> and <hi>Write,</hi> as fast as ever they can take it; and so she passes to the other parts of an <hi>Ingenuous Education</hi> with them. She is like another <hi>Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheba,</hi> always instilling into their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren something that is <hi>Wise</hi> and <hi>Good;</hi> and she keeeps up that <hi>Authority</hi> over them that they <hi>Fear</hi> as well as <hi>Love</hi> her; and they dare not <hi>Refuse</hi> what she shall <hi>Command.</hi> Unto her <hi>Instruction</hi> she also joyns an <hi>Inspection</hi> of them; so that she is very gravely <hi>Inquisitive</hi> into their Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, their Companies, their Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies: Nor will she spare <hi>Corrections</hi> where there Miscarriages do call for the <hi>Rod;</hi> and she will not <hi>overlay</hi> them with her Sinful Fondness, lest God make them <hi>Cross<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s</hi> to her, for her being afraid of <hi>Crossing</hi> them in their Exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancies. And besides the <hi>Example</hi> of all Virtue that she sets before them, she is frequently Praying with them, as well as for them, <hi>That they may be saved.</hi> She pursues the Lord with such Cries for her Children as the <hi>Canaanitess</hi> used, <hi>Lord, Heal my Child, that is annoy'd by a Devil!</hi> and such as <hi>Monica</hi> used for <hi>Aushtin,</hi> upon which a great Person said
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:206531:71"/> unto her, <hi>'Tis impossible that a Child of so many Tears should ever Perish!</hi> And she will carry them one after another alone into her Closet with her, where she do's wrestle with God for them all, professing <hi>I will not let thee go, except thou Bless them.</hi> Her Children being thus well <hi>Brought up,</hi> she will do as the Lady <hi>Cornelia</hi> did unto the Ladies who expected she would show them her <hi>Jewels,</hi> as they had shown her <hi>Theirs;</hi> even <hi>Bring forth her well Educated Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as her Jewels.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">VI. If she meets with any <hi>Disasters</hi> in her Children, by her <hi>Patience</hi> and her <hi>Piety</hi> she turns them into <hi>Benefits.</hi> 'Tis possible her <hi>Children</hi> may <hi>Sin,</hi> but this causes her presently to reflect upon the Errors of her own <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> and especially upon any defect in her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct unto <hi>them;</hi> So she is put upon <hi>The Repentance which is not to be Repented of.</hi> 'Tis also possible her <hi>Children</hi> may <hi>Die,</hi> but she is not then like the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed Women of <hi>Bethlehem, Weeping for their Children, and not willing to be Comforted because they are not.</hi> Instead of saying like <hi>Jacob, All these are against me;</hi> she rather says with <hi>Joseph,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:206531:71"/> God may mean it unto God.</hi> She do's not Roar like a Beast, and Howl, <hi>I cannot bear it;</hi> but she rather says, <hi>I can take any thing well at the hands of God.</hi> She follows them to the Grave as a very moderate Mourner, with <hi>Hopes</hi> that God is carrying on the Everlasting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs of <hi>His Grace</hi> in <hi>her Soul</hi> by these Dispensations; and with <hi>Hopes</hi> that <hi>their Souls</hi> are gone to be <hi>With Christ, which is by far the best of all.</hi> She look'd upon her Children as meer <hi>Loans</hi> from God, which he may call for when he please; and she quietly submits, if God say, <hi>Give them up, you have have had them long enough!</hi> Of old such as could not Encounter an Affliction patiently, were condemned therefore, <hi>To wear Womens Cloaths;</hi> but the <hi>Cloaths</hi> of our Good Woman, will not be a Bar to her bearing of <hi>this</hi> Affliction patiently. She parts with her Children in such Terms as <hi>Jerom</hi> on that occasion directs his Friends unto; <hi>Lord, thou hast now taken from me, the Children which thou hadst first given to me; I do not complain that thou dost now Receive them; I give Thanks that ever thou didst at first bestow them.</hi> She has already pluck'd out a
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:206531:72"/>
                        <hi>Right Eye,</hi> and cut off a <hi>Right Hand</hi> for God; and so she can readily part with another <hi>Limb</hi> at a call of his: Yea, though the <hi>Death</hi> were never so awful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly circumstanced, yet she says, <hi>The will of the Lord be done!</hi> And she will not let <hi>one Sorrow</hi> swallow up the sense of a Thousand, a Million of <hi>Mercies,</hi> but she approves the Temper of that Good Woman, who having <hi>Two</hi> Children by a violent stroak taken from her, hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somely took up the <hi>Third,</hi> and said, <hi>Blessed be God that has left me this!</hi> If they were <hi>Infant Children;</hi> whereof she is bereaved, she <hi>Assures</hi> her self, that the Lord is <hi>their God,</hi> and so they can't be miserable. No, <hi>Let me go to them,</hi> (saith she) <hi>They shan't return to me.</hi> If they were <hi>Adult Children,</hi> she <hi>Comforts.</hi> her self that they might have <hi>The Root of the Matter</hi> in them, under whatever Clods of <hi>Airiness</hi> or <hi>Bashfulness</hi> it might have been concealed; and that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever suspicious marks might have been upon them, they might seek and find mercy, <hi>Between the Stirrup and the Ground.</hi> So she takes that Counsel, <hi>Refrain thy Voice from Weeping, and thine
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:206531:72"/> Eyes from Tears, for thy Work shall be Rewarded.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This is the Virtuous MOTHER; And she is one that also counts her <hi>Servants</hi> to be after a sort her <hi>Children</hi> too: She <hi>Guides</hi> the <hi>House</hi> according to her Office prescribed by the Apostle; so that with a <hi>Motherly</hi> Deportment unto them, with an Obliging, but yet Reserved Carriage towards them, and with a Charitable Regard unto the Everlasting Welfare of their Souls: You may see her acquitting her self ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more as a <hi>Virtuous Mistress</hi> likewise in the Family. But there is danger lest she become a <hi>Widdow</hi> before she die; if she do, let us now take notice of her Frame and Mein, in the Sorrowful Condition that is now come upon her.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The Virtuous WIDOW.</head>
                     <p>THE Vast Numbers of Poor <hi>Widows</hi> in every Neighbourhood, make it very suspicious that our <hi>Virtuous Mother</hi> may at some time or other tast the Sad, Sowre, Tear-ful <hi>Cup</hi> of <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow-hood.</hi> If this be the <hi>Portion of her
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:206531:73"/> Cup,</hi> we must suppose that she gives her Husband a <hi>Decent Burial;</hi> that is, as on the one side, a Funeral that shall not be <hi>below</hi> his Figure, so on the other side, a Funeral that shall not be <hi>above</hi> her E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state; and while she dislikes the expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive Humours of <hi>Poland,</hi> where two or three Funerals coming one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, are so extravagantly Chargable as to Ruine a whole Family: She ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheless will give as Honourable an <hi>Enterment</hi> as ever she can to the <hi>Forsaken Mansion</hi> of the <hi>Soul</hi> which was dearer to her than the World.</p>
                     <p>Conceiving our <hi>Virtuous Woman</hi> to have her <hi>Widows</hi> Vail upon her, we may behold her demeaning her self as a most <hi>Virtuous</hi> Person in it.</p>
                     <p n="1">I. Her <hi>Grief</hi> on the Death of her Husband is <hi>Great,</hi> and yet <hi>Wise,</hi> and as <hi>Wisely Great</hi> as <hi>Greatly Wise.</hi> Her Mourning is more like a still <hi>Rain,</hi> than a loud <hi>Storm;</hi> and instead of <hi>Bellowing Passions</hi> which usually moulder aawy into a total and the coldest Forgetfulness, faster than the Corpse of the Husband in the Grave; she has a <hi>Silent</hi> but a <hi>Lasting</hi> sorrow; and yet that sorrow moderated by a Filial Submission to the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:206531:73"/> hand of that Glorious God, before whom she <hi>Opens not her Mouth</hi> any more than humbly to say, <hi>Lord, thou didst it.</hi> She will not by intemperate <hi>Vexations</hi> and <hi>Afflictions</hi> of her self, make her self like the Frantick Women in the <hi>East-Indies,</hi> which burn themselves to Death in the Fire wherein they consume the Dead-Bodies of their Husbands; but yet she calls her self <hi>Marah,</hi> saying, <hi>The Lord has dealt bitterly with me!</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">II. It is now her main study and solace to have an Interest in that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, <hi>Isa 54. 5. Thy Maker is thy Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</hi> And therefore like her whom the Apostle calls <hi>A Widow indeed,</hi> she <hi>Trust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in God, and continueth in Supplications and Prayers Night and Day.</hi> She consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders her self as now more than ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the <hi>Family of God;</hi> with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion that he will certainly and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Provide for her. Hence also the time that she formerly spent in <hi>Conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> with her Husband, she now spends in <hi>Sutplication</hi> to, and <hi>Meditation</hi> on her God; and by an extraordinary <hi>Devotion,</hi> she seeks to find all that in the Alsuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient JESUS, which may repair the absence of the best Husband upon
<pb facs="tcp:206531:74"/> Earth. She is an <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> or one to whom the <hi>Fulness of God</hi> in the <hi>Promise of God</hi> is enough.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, if she be capable of st, she will now more abound in all the Exercises of <hi>Charity</hi> towards her needy Neighbours; whether she have the Name of <hi>Alice</hi> or no, yet according to the signification of it, She'll be <hi>Noble:</hi> And she will be an <hi>Helena,</hi> or an <hi>Eleanor,</hi> which is to say, as much as <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful:</hi> Her <hi>Visits,</hi> her <hi>Bounties,</hi> and her <hi>Succcours</hi> to the poor are now increased rather than abated, with her new <hi>Leifure</hi> for them; and if she be a Person of <hi>Quality,</hi> she becomes yet more excellent for this <hi>Quality</hi> - What is a <hi>Lady</hi> in true and old English, but a <hi>Loaf dian,</hi> that is, <hi>A Bread server?</hi> Or one that will give <hi>Loafs</hi> of Bread unto the Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. She is both an <hi>Anna a Widow which departs not from the Temple, but serves God with Fastings and Prayers Night and Day;</hi> and a <hi>Dorcas, A Widow full of Good Works and Alms-Deeds.</hi> Thus will she to better purpose than once another Woman did, explain the Riddle of <hi>Sampson</hi> by finding <hi>Honey in a Carcase:</hi> Promoting the Life of <hi>her
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:206531:74"/> own Soul,</hi> by the <hi>Death</hi> of him whom she loved as <hi>her own Soul.</hi> Much less will she ever venture to do any thing <hi>unworthy</hi> the <hi>Character</hi> and <hi>Relation</hi> of that <hi>Petson</hi> (if he were a <hi>Worthy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi>) whose <hi>Relict</hi> she is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</p>
                     <p n="3">III. She reckons that she must now be <hi>Father</hi> as well as <hi>Mother</hi> to the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans</hi> with whom she is left Entrusted; and their <hi>Fathers</hi> beloved Image on them, dos farther Augment, yea, Double her Care concernlng them. While her Husband was <hi>Alive</hi> she still acted as a <hi>Deputy Husband,</hi> for the maintaining of all good Orders in the House, when he was out of the way. And now her Husband is <hi>Deceas'd,</hi> she thinks that upon the Setting of the <hi>Sun,</hi> the <hi>Moon</hi> is to Govern; and there shall not be one Prayer the less performed, or one Fault the more indulged among her poor Lambs, because he is gone. The <hi>Kindred</hi> of her Expired Husband are also still welcome and grateful to her, upon his Account. But she is now particularly more Sollicitous than ever to teach her <hi>Children</hi> how to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that Favour of God, <hi>When my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:206531:75"/> is gone, the Lord shall take me up.</hi> Some Women have the Names of Men a little altered, as <hi>Jaquet</hi> (from <hi>Jacoba) Joanna, Joan, Jane, Jennet</hi> (all from <hi>John.) Thomasin, Philippa, Frances, Henrietta, Antonia, Julian, Dionysià,</hi> and the like. But all our Widows are thus put upon doing the <hi>Works</hi> of Men; may their God help them!</p>
                     <p n="4">IV. She is not Forward and Hasty now to take the Liberty which the Scripture does <hi>Give</hi> unto <hi>Younger Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows;</hi> that is, <hi>to Marry.</hi> While she has one <hi>Eye Weeping</hi> for her Departed Husband, she has not the other <hi>open</hi> to see <hi>Who comes next?</hi> Nor will she think an <hi>Ephesian Matron</hi> a fit Copy for her. She counts it no hard Law, which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Ancient <hi>Pagans</hi> kept with great severity; <hi>That no Widow should Marry within Ten or Twelve Months after the Death of her Husband:</hi> And she won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that any <hi>Christians</hi> ordinarily can <hi>Marry sooner.</hi> If she had a <hi>Good</hi> Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, his <hi>Memory</hi> has been so Embal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with her, that she cannot presently make room in her Affections for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. If she had a <hi>bad</hi> Husband, the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:206531:75"/> Cross felt so heavy, that she will be <hi>Slow</hi> to be <hi>Sure</hi> that it been't renew'd upon her. But if after a convenient stay she do <hi>Marry,</hi> it shall be, <hi>Only in the Lord;</hi> unto a Man that shall be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Heretical</hi> in his Principles, nor <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant</hi> in his Practices; and unto one that may be <hi>proper</hi> for her. Wherefore also if she be very <hi>Old,</hi> she will not without special causes marry one that is very <hi>Young;</hi> suspecting that such a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Lover may Court <hi>Hers</hi> more than <hi>Her;</hi> and that if there be too much (as perhaps a score of years) Ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality of <hi>Age,</hi> it may otherwise <hi>Prove</hi> as Temptatious, as it <hi>Looks</hi> Indecent. Indeed <hi>Jerom</hi> tells us of an Old man at <hi>Rome</hi> who had Buried Twenty Wives, which he took one after the Death of t'other; and that he then took the Twenty first, who also had Buried Nineteen Husbands; but methings they were an <hi>Ʋgly Couple.</hi> And the Woman whereof <hi>Buxtorf</hi> relates in his <hi>Talmudic Lexicon,</hi> that she Buried <hi>Eleven Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands,</hi> and had then an Epitaph of <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Verses</hi> bestowed upon her self, deserved sure the last stroak of her Epitaph, which was to this purpose,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:206531:76"/>
                        <hi>A Woman fit to have no Bed but a Cold Grave.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">V. When she is <hi>Match'd</hi> unto a <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Husband,</hi> whom she will never twit with any Reflecting and Uncomely Remembrances of her <hi>First;</hi> She is more than ordinarily sollicitous to be <hi>A Good Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>her-in-Law,</hi> if she must be one at all; and so do her part for the removing of those <hi>Imputations</hi> which <hi>Mother-in-Law</hi> have generally laboured under. She knows that the way for her to have the Blessing of Heaven upon <hi>Her</hi> Children, is for her to make her self a Blessing to <hi>His;</hi> and Unkindnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses to the <hi>Motherless</hi> little Birds which now call her <hi>their Dam,</hi> will certainly be repay'd by the Just Revenges of God. She is therefore so far from the partiality of that <hi>Mother-in-Law,</hi> who when her own Child hurt a Child of her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands by throwing of a Stone, <hi>Whipped the Child that felt the Stone, for standing in the way of the Child that slung it;</hi> that she makes no observable difference between <hi>his</hi> Children and <hi>hers;</hi> unless it be <hi>This,</hi> that she Corrects <hi>hers</hi> her self, and refers <hi>his</hi> to him; and yet for her at any time to inform her Husband of
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:206531:76"/> any ill Manners in <hi>his</hi> Children, is a thing whereto she has an <hi>Aversion</hi> so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream, that she will never do it, unless upon extream <hi>Necessity.</hi> Indeed she Essays to be such a Wife unto him, that she may not merit the Name which the <hi>Second Wise</hi> of <hi>Lamech</hi> had; Namely, <hi>Zillah,</hi> or, but <hi>A Shadow</hi> of a Wife: Much less would she be as the <hi>First</hi> of them was called, an <hi>Anah,</hi> that is, <hi>An Affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>cter</hi> to him.</p>
                     <p n="6">VI. At length <hi>Old Age</hi> comes upon her; and <hi>Prisca,</hi> or <hi>Priscilla,</hi> that is. <hi>An Old Woman,</hi> is her Title; but by an <hi>Hoary Head found in the way of Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> it is that she now Challenges the Honour of <hi>A Saint,</hi> even from those abusive Tongues, which use to traduce for <hi>A Witch,</hi> every <hi>Old Woman,</hi> whose Temper with her Visage is not emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently Good. She thoroughly studies every particle of the Apostolical Charge, <hi>That the Aged Women, be in behaviour as becometh Holiness; not make bates, not given to much wine, Teachers of good things; That they may Teach the Young Women:</hi> And the nearer she comes to her <hi>End,</hi> the more acquainted she is with <hi>Him that is from the Beginning.</hi> She is not impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:206531:77"/> of being Esteemed <hi>Old;</hi> and styled <hi>Bilhah,</hi> that is, <hi>Fading;</hi> nor do's it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend her, as once an English Queen, to be told that, <hi>That Age hath sprinkled its Meal upon her Head.</hi> But she keeps long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Day, when the Lord Jesus will send his Angels to fetch her unto the Regions of Everlasting Light and Life, and keeps wishing <hi>Oh come Lord Jesus!</hi> till she arrive to be <hi>For ever with the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This is a Virtuous WIDOW. God grant that our <hi>Widows</hi> may not be <hi>Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply' d;</hi> but for them that <hi>are,</hi> God grant that they may be thus <hi>Virtuous! That</hi> is it which will render them all <hi>Jochebeds,</hi> which is, <hi>Most Glorious Ones.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I now Praise thee, O my God for thy Assisting my Endeavours to describe the Praises of the Virtuous Woman; and rely upon thy Grace in thy Son, that these my poor Labours may be Accepted and Succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among the Daughters of thy People.</hi> AMEN.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:206531:77"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed for <hi>Tho▪ Parhurst</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapside.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Confirming Work of Religion, and its great things made plain by their primary evidences and demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: whereby the meanest in the Church may soon be made able to render a rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal account of their Faith.</p>
            <p>The Present Aspect of our Times, and of the Extraordinary Conjunction of things therein; in a rational view and prospect of the same, as it respects the publick hazard and safety of <hi>Brittain</hi> in this day. These two last by <hi>Rob. Fleming,</hi> Author of the fulfilling of the Scriptures, and Minister at <hi>Rotterdam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>England</hi>'s Allarm: Being an account of Gods most considerable dispensations of Judgment and Mercy towards these King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, for fourteen years last past; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so of the several sorts of Sins and Sinners therein: especially the Murmurers against this Present Government. With an Earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est call to speedy Humiliation and Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, &amp; Supplication, as the chief means of prospering their Majesties Councils and Preparations. Dedicated to the King and Queen.</p>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:206531:78"/>
            <p>A Family Altar erected to the honour of the Eternal God: Or, a solemn Essay to promote the Worship of God in Private Houses: being some Meditations on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 5. 2, 3. With the Best Entail▪ or Dying Parents Living Hopes for their Surviving Children grounded upon the Covenant of Gods Grace with Believers and their Seed. Being a short Discourse on 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. 5. By <hi>Oliver Heywood</hi> Minister of the Gospel.</p>
            <p>The Gospel Mystery of Sanctification open'd in sundry practical Directions, suited especially to the Case of those who labour under the guilt and power of Indwelling Sin. To which is added a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of Justification. By <hi>Walter Marshal</hi> Minister of the Gospel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Death improved, and immoderate for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for deceased Friends and Relations reproved. Wherein you have many ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments against Immoderate sorrow, and many profitable Lessons which we may learn from such Providences; by <hi>E. Bury,</hi> formerly Minister of great <hi>Bolas</hi> in <hi>Shrop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> Author of the Help to Holy Walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; the Husbandmans Companion <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Poor mans help and Young mans guide: containing, 1. Doctrinal instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:206531:78"/> for the right informing of his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 2. Practical directions▪ for the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral course of his Life. 3. Particular advices for the well managing of every day with reference to his natural actions: Civil Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, Necessary Recreations, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Duties, particularly Prayer, Publick in the Congregation, Private in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, Secret in the Closet, Reading the Holy Scriptures, Hearing the Word Preached, and Receiving the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. By <hi>Will. Burkitt.</hi> M. A. of <hi>Pembrook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and now Vicar of <hi>Dedham</hi> in <hi>Essex,</hi> and Author of the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Discourse of Infant Baptism.</p>
            <p>A Plain Discourse about rash and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Anger; as a help for such as are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be relieved against so sad and too generally prevailing a distemper even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst professors of Religion; being the substance of some Sermons Preached at <hi>Manchester.</hi> By <hi>Hen. Newcome</hi> M. A. and Minister of the Gospel there, and Author of the Improvement of Sickness.</p>
            <p>The Rod or the Sword, the present <hi>Dilemma</hi> of the Nations of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> considered, argued and improved on <hi>Ezek</hi> 21. 14. by a true friend to the Protestant Interest, and the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Government.</p>
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:206531:79"/>
            <p>A Present for such as have been Sick and are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered: Or, a Discourse concerning the Good that comes out of the Evil of Affliction: being several Sermons Preached after his being raised from a Bed of Languishing. <hi>By Nathaniel Vincent</hi> M. A. and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Conversion as the Soul. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rue Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone of Grace and Nature. Discourse of Conscience Treatise of Prayer and Love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some passages in the Holy Life and Death of the Late Reverend Mr. <hi>Edmund Trench,</hi> most of them drawn out of his own Diary. Published by <hi>Joseph Boyse</hi> Minister in <hi>Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Advice to an only Child, or Excellent Council to all young Persons containing the sum and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of Experimental and Practical Divinity. Written by an Eminent and Judicious Divine, for the Private Use of an Only Child; now made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick for the benefit of all.</p>
            <p>An Account of the Blessed Trinity argued from the Nature and Perfection of the Supream Spirit co-incident with the Scripture Doctrine, in all the Articles of the Catholick-Creeds; together with its Mystical, Faederal and Practical Uses in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion. By <hi>William Borrough</hi> Rector of <hi>Cheyns</hi> in <hi>Bucks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Discourse of Justification being the sum of twenty Sermons by <hi>Walter Cross,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>Practical Discourses on Sickness and Recovery.</p>
            <p>A Discourse concerning Trouble of Mind, in Three parts by <hi>Tim. Rogers,</hi> M. A. There is now in the Press a Treatise of Consolation by the same Author.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:206531:79"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>